<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Armin Ronacher's Thoughts and Writings</title>
  <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom</id>
  <updated>2008-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/" />
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Armin Ronacher's personal blog about programming, games and random thoughts that come to his mind.</subtitle>
  <generator>Werkzeug</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Apologies to Github</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2008/9/20/apologies-to-github</id>
    <updated>2008-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2008/9/20/apologies-to-github" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I wrote a &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;/2008/9/14/bitbucket-is-no-bit-bucket/&quot;&gt;review about bitbucket&lt;/a&gt;
and one part of the blog post was about how I was annoyed by the GitHub
admins forcing people into using GitHub for hosting. Here the section in
all its shaming glory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
When GitHub appeared on the internets for the first time, there was
a short period of time when I saw the admins of that site jump into
many IRC channels of projects that were using git already to switch
to GitHub for hosting.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that either my mind played a trick on me, or I screwed up
earlier and mixed up persons. Fortunately IRC logs exist to disprove
what I wrote earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the discussions I could grep in my IRC logs it were always non GitHub
administrators that tried to convince the project owners to switch to
GitHub and in one situation it was one GitHub author that &lt;em&gt;briefly&lt;/em&gt;
joined the discussion to explain the benefits of GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I screwed up and my negative bias towards GitHub was mostly based on
something my mind made up. Because of that I want to apologise to the
GitHub team for the false claims I made earlier. I hope I can somehow
made up for that somehow.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

