<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Armin Ronacher's Thoughts and Writings</title>
  <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom</id>
  <updated>2009-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/" />
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Armin Ronacher's personal blog about programming, games and random thoughts that come to his mind.</subtitle>
  <generator>Werkzeug</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">The Sad State of MySQL Python</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2009/1/8/the-sad-state-of-mysql-python</id>
    <updated>2009-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2009/1/8/the-sad-state-of-mysql-python" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I admit it. I was a friend of &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://mysql.org/&quot;&gt;MySQL&lt;/a&gt;. Two years
ago MySQL was the only database server I was using at all. Lately
however I replaced nearly all applications that were still using MySQL
with postgres and even SQLite. One of the applications that is still
using MySQL is &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://ubuntuusers.de/inyoka/&quot;&gt;Inyoka&lt;/a&gt;, the portal
software deployed &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://ubuntuusers.de/&quot;&gt;ubuntuusers&lt;/a&gt;. For reasons
you don't want to know we are unable to switch the deployment setup from
MySQL to postgres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that would be fine if &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://sourceforge.net/projects/mysql-python&quot;&gt;mysql-python&lt;/a&gt; aka &lt;cite&gt;MySQLdb&lt;/cite&gt; would not
suck so much. Besides not supporting the latest MySQL features it also
leaks memory a lot. A friend of mine who discovered the problem, noticed
a couple of lost megabytes the minute on ubuntuusers — that's a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That problem seems to be fixed in the SVN trunk but the latest activity
there was more than 9 months ago which is a problem. Neither the
cheeseshop`^W^W`pypi has non-leaking packages, also not Linux
distributions such as debian or ubuntu. The &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://mysql-python.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;development blog&lt;/a&gt; was last updated in May of 2008
which makes me even more concerned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I wonder if anyone has experience with the MySQL library and the
Python API to take over the development. I guess there are still some
MySQL users left, even though the project has an incredible bad
reputation lately &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://monty-says.blogspot.com/2008/11/oops-we-did-it-again-mysql-51-released.html&quot;&gt;due to problems in the release management&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a temporary workaround I can recommend either updating to the trunk
version (which seems to be unstable according to one of the last commit
messages) or disable unicode support where the leak apparently is. Nice
libraries such as &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://sqlalchemy.org/&quot;&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/a&gt; can convert
bytestrings to unicode automatically on their own as well if you &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.sqlalchemy.org/trac/wiki/DatabaseNotes#MySQL&quot;&gt;tell
them to&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

