<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Armin Ronacher's Thoughts and Writings</title>
  <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-11-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/" />
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Armin Ronacher's personal blog about programming, games and random thoughts that come to his mind.</subtitle>
  <generator>Werkzeug</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">A Case for Upserts</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2014/2/16/a-case-for-upserts</id>
    <updated>2014-02-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2014/2/16/a-case-for-upserts" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It looks like upserts yet again will not land in Postgres.  This is deeply
unsatisfying because over the last couple of years it has become more than
obvious for me that this functionality is not just useful but a necessity.
Interestingly enough it seems like a lot of people are suggesting that
depending on upserts means that the design of the application is bad but I
would argue that anything other than upserts means that the application is
actually deeply unreliable or badly planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;what-s-an-upsert&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's an Upsert&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upserts probably got a bad reputation because they were popularized by
MySQL which is often regarded as a bad SQL database.  However MySQL also
became popular as a driving force behind web applications so some of its
design decisions work really well in a web environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In MySQL there are two types of upserts: replaces (which can be emulated
in Postgres) and the &amp;quot;on duplicate&amp;quot; clause which can be used to react on
an already existing row.  The latter is really hard to efficiently
implement in Postgres at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will go into the details of why upserts are important in a bit, I just
want to show the two types of it first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;replaces&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Replaces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple upsert in MySQL Is the replace insert.  It's an insert that
will implicitly delete an already existing row before it does anything.
The way it's implemented is an extension to the insert syntax:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;into&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;key&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;value&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an alternative syntax that works similar to updates (which to be
fair, MySQL also has for &lt;cite&gt;insert&lt;/cite&gt; and which I find much pleasant because
it mirrors the update syntax):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;key&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;value&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way both of these work is by inserting a value and deleting an already
existing record for a given primary key or unique constraint.  The most
common case for this safely treating a table as a key value store.  In
this particular case you can also use a transaction safely in Postgres and
you can just send a delete before the insert:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;where&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;key&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;into&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;key&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;value&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;commit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious problem with this however is that a transaction that happens
concurrently will not see the row any more.  You can easily test this by
just not committing and attempting to update from another shell.  The
update will block until the commit happens but once it finishes it will
tell you that zero rows were updated even though there were clearly rows
available to update.  The reason for this is that transactions just
serialize the execution, they don't guarantee any atomicity of independent
row updates.  After the delete happens the second transaction gets a
chance to run and the update will fail because it no longer sees a row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you're thinking the solution is to just raise the isolation level,
you're in for a disappointment.  Even with the highest isolation level the
result is the same.  However an explicit table lock gets around this.  To
be honest, this probably has the same characteristics as doing the same
operation on MyISAM where MySQL got its initial upserts from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;lock&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;exclusive&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;where&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;key&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;into&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my_table&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;key&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;value&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;commit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will work and still allow concurrent reads, but it will definitely
block any concurrent modifications from happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;on-duplicate-clauses&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Duplicate Clauses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more interesting upsert in MySQL is the &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;ON DUPLICATE KEY UPDATE&lt;/tt&gt;
clause.  For some reason this got a bad reputation similar to basic's &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;on
error resume next&lt;/tt&gt; even though it's not just useful but also the only
safe way to handle concurrency with uniques.  The way it works is by
defining an insert as well as an update in the same statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance this is the way to implement safe counters that are not
initialized upfront:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;into&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;counters&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;counter_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;my_counter&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duplicate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;update&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the key &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;'my_counter'&lt;/tt&gt; does not exist yet, the row is created by
inserting it with the value &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;1&lt;/tt&gt; for &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/tt&gt; otherwise it will execute
the update statement on that particular row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious question what happens if there are two unique
constraints on a table, and the answer is quite simply that it breaks down
in that case.  If there are two uniques MySQL will not give an error but
just execute the operation as if it was happening on the first row that
matches.  Essentially the where is extended to be be an or for any of the
unique constraints compared to the values from the insert statement.  This
is obviously dangerous and definitely not optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a purely theoretical case the better way would be to be explicit about
the uniqueness.  This could work like this (if a database would support
it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;into&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;counters&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;counter_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;my_counter&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duplicate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;counter_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;update&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;seq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard SQL way is to be super explicit about everything and very
confusing &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merge_%28SQL%29&quot;&gt;MERGE STATEMENT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;why-upserts&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Upserts?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why are upserts important?  The reason is concurrency.  Without an
upsert there is no way to reliably ensure that a row is in a certain
state.  The only workaround is to move the code that creates the row into
a locked (or semi locked) situation.  For instance the traditional example
of a one-to-one relationship is usually solved in postgres by just
ensuring the related inserts have low chance of concurrency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine for instance you have users and user settings.  Each row in the
users table has also a related row in the user settings table but each
user can only ever have one.  Since users typically only ever register
once you can just hope for the best and just do an insert.  In case there
is some concurrency happening then the second transaction will just fail
with a unique constraint failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reason this is a problem is because of lazy creation, network
failure and the hope to make all operations idempotent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;lazy-creation&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lazy Creation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lazy creation is the obvious example of where the lack of upserts is
painful.  The counter example was already brought up.  In this case a
counter gets created on first increment but that's by far not the only
example.  A much more common case is functionality that did not exist at a
certain point in time and is related to bulk data already existing or is
just inherently optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance say you have a few million users and all the sudden you want
to add a new one-to-one relationship for these users.  Say for instance
you added a new notification feature and you want to store the
notification settings in a new table.  If you don't have upserts the only
way to safely deal with this is to have a migration script that adds a
nulled-out row for each of these users at the time you add this feature to
your application.  This is expensive and ultimately a waste of space,
because many of your users will already be inactive at the time you add
this feature.  Also not all of those users will actually use
notifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obviously better way is an upsert: create this row when the user first
needs to configure the notification settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;network-failure-and-idempotency&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Network Failure and Idempotency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upserts are especially important for web applications because the network
is inherently unreliable.  It's true that HTTP is implemented on top of
TCP, a reliable transport, but obviously there is one case that TCP (or
HTTP) cannot do by themselves: bidirectional acknowledgement of high level
operations.  An operation is idempotent if it can be applied multiple
times without changing the outcome.  An example of such an operation is
any read-only operation (such as selects).  It does not matter how many
times you select something, it will still give you the same result.  While
the data returned for the next select might be slightly different because
of concurrent updates, the select itself does not modify the data.
Another inherently idempotent operation is obviously a deletion.  No
matter how many times you delete something, in the end the row is always
gone.  Again, someone might concurrently re-create the row but that does
not make the operation non-idempotent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand inserts, increments and similar things are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
idempotent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional example is usually brought up with purchases but really
this problem is not unique to purchases: it can happy for every single
non-idempotent HTTP request.  Say you click the purchase button but an
error occurs: is it safe to submit the payment again or not?  How would
you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple answer is that you cannot know because of late failure on the
network.  For instance say there was a badly implemented web store and a
user clicks on the submit button and ultimately the website times out or
the user gets a connection reset message.  However as far as the server
was concerned the request was made, the record for the payment was
recorded, the transaction was committed and the user was redirect to a
result page and the connection was closed after sending the data.
Unfortunately all of this went through a proxy server and the proxy server
barfed when sending the data back to the client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to make such an operation idempotent is to provide extra
information with the initial request to be able to detect a duplicate
attempt.  The very obvious one is a &amp;quot;nonce&amp;quot;.  When the client shows the
payment page it rolls a large random number.  With the purchase the user
submits this number and the server will permanently store it.  Even if the
response to the client fails, the client can safely retry the transmission
under the assumption he sends the same number to the server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server can then look if the nonce was already stored in the database
and then not carry out the payment a second time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unfortunate truth is that network failure is very, very common and
can really happen for every single HTTP request.  The reason people mostly
bring it up with payments is because it's the part where you can lose the
most amount distrust in customers.  If you charge someone twice for a
service you can only deliver once you have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;constraint-failures&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Constraint Failures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upserts do not solve this problem, but upserts make it much easier to deal
with the problem of resubmission in a generic way.  A unique constraint
gets you quite far, but it means that all code needs to be able to deal
with a constraint failure.  For instance to go back to the example of
notification settings.  If each user can only have one notification
setting page, then what happens if accidental concurrency happens and one
of the two transactions fails with a unique constraint failure?  Not
handling it will cause an internal server error most likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how would code respond to this?  The obvious one is to try the insert
first, and then if a constraint failure happens to retry the transaction
with an update.  However this does not solve the problem, because a
concurrent delete might now all the sudden make your update fail.  So if
deletes are allowed, you now need to check if the update worked, and go
back to an insert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ultimately is loop that endlessly retries and has not guarantee of
ever succeeding if high concurrency happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;upserts-are-hard&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Upserts are Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been brought up multiple times that upserts are hard to implement
in Postgres because there is no efficient way to resolve the concurrency.
This is true, because the only solution currently is to lock the whole
table which has a wide range of problems.  Unfortunately this problem does
not go away if you tell the client to solve it.  People tried many things
to work around it (CTEs which are inherently not concurrency safe, stored
procedures with endless loops, loops on the client through savepoints
etc., denormalization from an immutable append only log of modification)
and all of these solutions are terrible for various reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Postgres would implement a shitty and inefficient version of an upsert
statement at the very worst it could be as bad as the current
implementation that people write on their own and then at least, there is
an established syntax and a way to improve it further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm deeply disappointed that this will again slip a Postgres release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a person not involved in the Postgres development I can't get rid of
the feeling that the main reason this is not progressing is because there
is a lot of emphasis to implement it in a standard compliant way through
the MERGE syntax instead of doing it through a proprietary and restricted
syntax extension in Postgres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unfortunate through is that Postgres is currently the only database
that does not have an upsert like functionality.  Even SQLite has some
workarounds by using a join in its replace into clause which is probably
good enough given the limited functionality it needs to provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I miss upserts.  A lot.  I just wish that more focus would be put on this
topic, especially now that Postgres is being more and more used as a
replacement for MongoDB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">A Europe For Our Children</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/5/18/for-our-children</id>
    <updated>2016-05-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/5/18/for-our-children" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most of the readers of this blog are not from Europe, let alone Austria,
the country I was born in.  As such I'm not sure how many will actually
care about Austrian politics here, especially if it's a lengthy post.  But
I would still like if you read it because I think the topic is important
and not just because of Austria.  Our problems here are not just ours,
they are a general issue that affects all of Europe and the western world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since you are probably in no way familiar with Austrian politics or the
situation in the country I want to give you a brief overview.  Austria has
recovered very quickly from the war torn country it was after World War 2
and emerged as one of the most powerful economies of Europe if looked at
on a GDP per capita basis.  It underwent a conversion from an agricultural
country with some tourism attached to being dominated by the service
industry and producing technology and parts (the economical tree map looks
confusing because it's so heavily diversified).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However as great as the country has developed after the wars and as
profitable the creation of the Eurozone was, there was an end to this
positive trend and it came with the financial crisis of 2007/2008
(although with a bit of a delay).  The economy did recover, but it did not
do it to the extent people wanted.  At the same time necessary reforms
were not implemented (or not implemented in the right ways) and as a
result the country has suffered major blows in the last few years.  From a
personal point of view I cannot stress enough how disappointed I am that
many of my collegues went to other countries and started their companies
there or work there.  But it would be foolish to blame politics on this
alone.  This is as much a problem of politics as it is a problem of
culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now reached the point where cheap and populist ideas like reducing
social welfare for non citizens gets popular support.  In this environment
right wing parties emerge and this sunday Austrians will probably elect
the first right wing leader of the country since the end of World War 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But politics not what I want to talk about.  What I want to talk about is
the erosion of civilized discourse in Austria and I think in all of
Europe.  A large part of the general public are unable to have civilized
discussions on the bases of facts and instead conspiracies and emotions
take over and this is something that extends to politicians in Austria as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-symptoms-and-problems&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Symptoms and Problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the emotional state of the country you can see a few
symptoms and problems that help the populists to raise to power:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inability (or unwillingness) to learn and understand&lt;/strong&gt; how Austria and
the world changed in the last few years.  I think this is a big one of the
people who want to leave the European Union and do similar crazy things
to the Austrian economy.  We're so intertwined with it, that I doubt
anyone can predict what would happen as a consequence of leaving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparing things that cannot directly be compared&lt;/strong&gt; is a very related
problem. As an example the Euro might have been a mistake for Germany
but that does not mean that the Euro was not a profit for Austria.  We
were pegged to the Mark before, for us not much changed.  If anything the
situation improved because we're an export nation and our export partners
are other European countries and if they also use the Euro they cannot
harm our exports by devaluing their own currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But despite the fact it's so very hard to compare countries because they
are so fundamentally differently structured - yet people will still do
it in conversations.  Switzerland is heralded as the great example of
continental Europe in Austria but it's so specific out of history that
it's incredible hard to copy or imitate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not being able consider the other side&lt;/strong&gt;. I am shocked sometimes what
people here in Austria think the US are like.  The idea that both
Europeans and Americans might have very similar fears or hopes for TTIP
for instance does not seem to exist here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of change&lt;/strong&gt;. I think this is a typical Austrian problem but to
smaller extent it probably exists elsewhere too. Everything new is
torpedoed until it cannot be avoided any more because every single other
country already did it before. That applies to smoking bans as much as
to embracing of credit cards, online services, acceptance of
homosexuality, Sunday shopping, flexible working hours and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broad categorization&lt;/strong&gt;. I think Austrians are masters at giving
good/bad labels to large masses of people based on some categorization
instead of considering the individual.  Refugees are either good or bad,
the industry is good or bad, corporations are good or bad, immigrants
are good or bad. That individually a refugee could be good or bad is
impossible to comprehend in the general discourse and if someone does
bring it up, it often gets dismissed as an outlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inability to give credit&lt;/strong&gt;. This is particularly a problem in Austrian
politics. It's one party against the other and never ever would a ruling
party give an opposition party credit or the other way round. Likewise
would social democratic voters never give conservative parties credit
for something or the other way round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-root-causes&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Root Causes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what causes this behavior?  I think Austria's history has a lot to do
with it.  In the recent history there were conservatives versus social
democrats.  Combined with the fact that after the war Austria emerged not
only as a loser but also has one with a lot of baggage due to the support
to national socialism and the complicated way to deal with it after the
war.  As such the population was always split in two on this level.
However they could unity at least somewhat by voting for one of the two
large centrist parties.  Because the country was doing really well, there
was no reason to reevaluate this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However when disaster struck this rift became bigger instead of smaller
and particular with this upcoming presidential election only the most
extreme candidates made it into the run-off. Voters did not vote for
people they believed in as much as they voted by using tactics against
predictions.  This now has lead to one the ugliest pre-elections I have
seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics are no longer about doing the right thing but defending
principles, even if they are completely unfounded.  Even though everybody
says they have the best for Austrian in mind everyone is so stuck to their
own opinion that not a single meter of compromise can be achieved.
Newspapers paint scary pictures of the different outcomes of the election,
how the country will be torn, how one candidate would mean European
sanctions and how the other candidate would mean the end of a functioning
society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;a-path-forward&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are clearly many things wrong in this country but so is it
everywhere else.  We're not alone with the changes in the world and we
cannot fall back to local solutions for these problems.  But likewise can
we not pretend that problems don't exist.  This behavior of ruling parties
has helped the rise of the populists.  It does not help to pretend that
immigration without integration does not contribute to problems in
society.  We need a more honest approach with more talking to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few days ago we got &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian_Kern&quot;&gt;a new chancellor&lt;/a&gt; and he has indicated that
he wants to end the course of confrontation his predecessors had.  This
has been supported by all other parties other than the right wing FPOe.  I
hope they reconsider and also want to constructively work together with
the rest of the government to lead the country forward and to restore a
positive way of thinking rather than the fear that has been going around
for the last years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This however is not something that is a problem that needs to be solved in
government.  This is a problem that we as people in that country have and
we need to talk to each other more.  If we talk more to each other I hope
it becomes clear that we share many core values, we just don't always
agree on all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to my friends in Austria: please vote. But more than that: please
accept that if the outcome is not what you wanted, that it does not mean
the end of the country as you know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">A Fresh Look at Rust</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2014/10/1/a-fresh-look-at-rust</id>
    <updated>2014-10-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2014/10/1/a-fresh-look-at-rust" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been programming with Rust for quite a long time now but that does
not mean much.  Rust has been changing for years now in such dramatic
ways that coming back after two months feels almost like working in a
different language.  One thing however never changed: the trajectory.
With every update, with every modification the whole thing became better
and better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is still no end to the changes in sight but it feels a lot more
stable now than a few months ago, and some API design patterns begin to
emerge.  I felt like now is a good time to explore this a bit more and
started to rewrite my &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://github.com/mitsuhiko/redis-rs&quot;&gt;redis library&lt;/a&gt; to fit better into the scope of
the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;where-is-rust-positioned&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where is Rust Positioned?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three languages where I do most of my work in are Python, C and C++.
To C++ I have a very ambivalent relationship because I never quite know
which part of the language I should use.  C is straightforward because the
language is tiny.  C++ on the other hand has all of those features where
you need to pick yourself a subset that you can use and it's almost
guaranteed that someone else picks a different one.  The worst part there
is that you can get into really holy wars about what you should be doing.
I have a huge hatred towards both the STL and boost and that has existed
even before I worked in the games industry.  However every time the topic
comes up there is at least someone who tells me I'm wrong and don't
understand the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust for me fits where &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; use Python, C and C++ but it fills that spot in
very different categories.  Python I use as language for writing small
tools as well as large scale server software.  Python there works well for
me primarily because the ecosystem is large and when it breaks it's a
super straightforward thing to debug.  It also keeps running and can
report if things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However one interesting thing about Python is that unlike many other
dynamic languages, Python feels very predictable.  For me this is largely
because I am a lot less dependent on the garbage collector than in many
other languages.  The reason for this is that Python for me means CPython
and CPython means refcounting.  I'm the guy who will go through your
Python codebase and break up cycles by introducing weak references.  Who
will put a refcount check before and after requests to make sure we're not
building up cycles.  Why?  Because I like when you can reason about what
the system is doing.  I'm not crazy and will disable the cycle collector
but I want it to be predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, Python is slow, Python has really bad concurrency support, the
interpreter is quite weak and it really feels like it should work
differently, but it does not cause me big problems.  I can start it and it
will still be there and running when I come back a month afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is in your face with memory and data.  It's very much like C and C++.
However unlike C and C++ it feels more like you're programming with Python
from the API point of view because of the type inference and because the
API of the standard library was clearly written with programmer
satisfaction in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;you-will-run-into-walls&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You will run into Walls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think an interesting thing about programming in Rust is that in the
beginning you will run into walls.  It's clearly not Python so lots of
things you can get away with in Python do not work in Rust.  At the same
time it's not C++ and the borrow checker will become your greatest enemy.
You will write some code and say: this stuff really should work, why do
you think you know better and stop me from doing this you stupid thing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that the borrow checker is not perfect.  The borrow checker
prevents you from doing dangerous things and it does that.  However it
often feels too restrictive.  In my experience though the borrow checker
actually is wrong much less often than you think it is and just requires
you to think a bit differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the borrow checker personally a lot.  I agree with that sometimes
you feel there should be a way to disable it, but when you think more
about it you are quite happy it's there.  The borrow checker prevents you
from building up some of the worst technical debt you can acquire, the
kind of debt which you can never repay.  The Python programming language
acquired a global interpreter lock when it got threading support and it
really required it ever since the language existed.  The interpreter was
written in a way that nowadays we are not sure how to make it concurrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you try, you can still make terrible decisions for concurrency in Rust,
but you really need to go out of your way to do it.  The language forces
you to think more and I believe that's a good thing.  I don't want to
become another &amp;quot;objective oriented programming is the billion dollar
mistake&amp;quot; preacher but I do think that the language decides largely what
code people write.  Because subclassing is easy in C++, Java, Python and
many more languages this is what we write.  And then birds are instances
of animal classes.  If you take that tool away you start thinking
differently and that's a good thing.  CPUs stop getting faster and looking
at one object at the time really no longer makes any sense at all.  We
need to start reasoning a lot more about collections of things and what
transformations we actually want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;rust-inspires&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rust Inspires&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me programming in Rust is pure joy.  Yes I still don't agree with
everything the language currently forces me to do but I can't say I have
enjoyed programming that much in a long time.  It gives me new ideas how
to solve problems and I can't wait for the language to get stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is inspiring for many reasons.  The biggest reason I like it is
because it's practical.  I tried Haskell, I tried Erlang and neither of
those languages spoke &amp;quot;I am a practical language&amp;quot; to me.  I know there are
many programmers that adore them, but they are not for me.  Even if I
could love those languages, other programmers would never do and that
takes a lot of enjoyment away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is something that anyone can pick up and it's fun all around.  First
of all (unless you hit a compiler bug) it won't crash on you.  It also
gives you nice error messages if it fails compiling.  Not perfect, but
pretty good.  It comes with a package manager that handles dependencies
for you, so you can start using libraries other people wrote without
having to deal with a crappy or non existing ecosystem.  Python got much
better over the years but packaging is still the biggest frustration
people have.  &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://crates.io/&quot;&gt;Cargo&lt;/a&gt; (rust's package manager) is
barely half a year old, but it has a full time developer on it and it's
fun to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even just the installation experience of the language is top notch.  It
gives you compiler + documentation tool + package manager and you're good
to go.  The fact alone that it has a documentation tool that spits out
beautifully looking documentation out of the box is a major contributor to
enjoying programming in it.  While I wish it had a bit more of Sphinx and
a bit less of javadoc, it's a really good start for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what's really inspiring about Rust are the small things.  When I first
played with Rust what amazed me the most was the good FFI support.  Not
only could you call into C libraries easily: it also found and linked them
for you.  There is so much more though and it's hidden everywhere.  There
is a macro (&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;include_str!&lt;/tt&gt;) that will read a file next to your source at
compile time into a string into your binary (How cool is that!?).  Not
only can you bake in contents of files, you can also pull environment
variables into your binaries for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;designing-apis&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Designing APIs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting part currently is definitely finding out how to
properly write APIs for Rust.  Rust as a language is undoubtedly more
complex than most other but thankfully not in a way that it overwhelms
you.  What makes Rust complex from an API point of view is that as a
programmer you feel a bit of a tension between writing the straightforward
code that you expect when programming in a systems language and providing
a nice high level API like you expect in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I feel making nice APIs is because the language encourages it.
First of all the language in itself is super expressive and it makes a lot
of fun to write things in it â€” on the other hand there is just so much
possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you an idea why it's fun to design APIs for Rust is that the type
system is just so damn good.  So Rust is statically type checked but it
has inference so you get away with writing really beautiful code.  In my
rust driver for instance, you can write code like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;extern&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;crate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;redis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;fn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;redis&lt;/span&gt;::&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Client&lt;/span&gt;::&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;redis://127.0.0.1/&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;unwrap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;con&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get_connection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;unwrap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;i32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;i32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;redis&lt;/span&gt;::&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;SET&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;42&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ignore&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;SET&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_2&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;43&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ignore&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;GET&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cmd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;GET&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;arg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_2&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;query&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;con&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;unwrap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;result = {}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you an idea how the same code looks in Python currently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;redis&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;redis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Redis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;127.0.0.1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;6379&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pipeline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pipe&lt;/span&gt; \
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;42&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; \
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_2&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;43&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; \
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; \
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;key_2&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;result = {}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;vm&quot;&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;__main__&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I find interesting about this is that the Rust library is nearly as
small and clear as the Python one, but is a much lower-level binding.
Unlike the Python library which gives each call a separate method, the
Rust library (because quite new) only wraps the low-level API and you need
to create the request manually by chaining calls for each argument.  Yet
the end result for a user is nearly as nice.  Granted there is extra
handling needed in Rust for the errors (which I avoided here a bit by
using &lt;cite&gt;unwrap&lt;/cite&gt; which makes the app terminate, but then the same is the
case in the Python version where I also miss error handling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cool thing though is that the Rust library is completely type safe.
And yet in total there are exactly &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; places where types are mentioned
and that's the same ones, where a cast to an integer was necessary in
Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This however is not the best we could do in Rust.  Rust has compiler
extensions which open up a whole range of possibilities.  For instance
there is a Rust library which statically verifies that Postgres SQL
commands are well formed: &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/sfackler/rust-postgres-macros&quot;&gt;rust-postgres-macros&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;literal-block&quot;&gt;
test.rs:8:26: 8:63 error: Invalid syntax at position 10: syntax error at or near &amp;quot;FORM&amp;quot;
test.rs:8     let bad_query = sql!(&amp;quot;SELECT * FORM users WEHRE name = $1&amp;quot;);
                                   ^~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
error: aborting due to previous error
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sort of stuff excites me a whole lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;If you're into API design in rust, join us in #rust-apidesign on the
Mozilla IRC network&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;rust-s-future&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rust's Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is Rust's memory tracking concept strong enough that we will accept it as a
valid programming model?  I am not sure.  I do believe though that Rust
can stand on its own feet already.  Even if it would turn out that the
borrow checker is not sound, I believe it would not hurt the language at
all to widespread adoption.  It's shaping up to be a really good language,
it works really well without GC and you can use it without a runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is an exceptionally good open source project.  And it needs more
helping hands.  The Windows support (while getting better) especially
needs more love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is interest in some more practical Rust experience I will
probably write something up about my experience making &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/mitsuhiko/redis-rs/&quot;&gt;redis-rs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">A Recap</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2011/1/1/recap</id>
    <updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2011/1/1/recap" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been reading a bunch of people's recaps of 2010.  I find that a
wonderful idea because it turns out that after a year you end up doing a
lot and don't appreciate it enough.  And it turns out, 2010 was an amazing
year.  This is my list of Open Source or programming related activities of
2010:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;docutils&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;January&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decided to learn game development.  This didn't go too well for a
while though.  I was kinda worn out of Python web development
after four years and wanted to do something new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;April&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made an April's fool joke web framework with a screencast that was
downloaded over 15.000 times.  Some people actually took it serious :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gave a talk about switching to Python 3 at the Linux days in Graz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Released Flask, a microframework based on my April's fool joke.  I
learned a lot from that, might be intresting for a talk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;May&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attended DjangoCon in Berlin and gave my first English talk ever.
It didn't go as well as it could have been but I was nervous
as fuck, especially because I was the first talk after the
keynote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;June&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started looking for a Job over the summer holidays and ended up
working with the guys from Lincoln Loop for a larger Django
project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sphinx made it into GSOC under the PSF umbrella and I am mentoring
a student again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;July&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attended EuroPython&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;August&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally diving into 3D engine development.  The books I bought a
few months back finally pay off and a painful dive into
mathematics starts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;September&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broke my macbook, needed replacement â€” expensive month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attended DjangoCon and met friends from Portland again.  Good
times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;October&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Held a talk at Pycon PL about new Python idioms.  Had the chance
to talk to finally meet Maciej Fijalkowski in person and a whole
bunch of interesting guys.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another talk about Good API Design in Kiev.  First time I was to
Ukraine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relaunched pocoo.org with a new design.  Looked for a bunch of
companies using pocoo Software and was proud seeing where our
stuff ended up beeing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;November&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got invited to ORD Camp 2011.  Feeling honored, but unfortunately
will not be able to attend :(&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;December&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;first last simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finally have something that looks rougly like a 3D voxel engine.
Still far from a game, but a start and with that project I learned
a whole lot that year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">About the Lack of Updates</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2012/8/27/about-the-lack-of-updates</id>
    <updated>2012-08-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2012/8/27/about-the-lack-of-updates" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you look over my contributions to my own open source projects over the
last six months you will have noticed that I became less active.  Why is
that?  There is no big conspiracy ongoing and I also don't plan on keeping
it this way, but there are two reasons for this.  The first one is that I
am now working for a computer game middleware company and we're using my
tools in production here.  The change in scenery caused me to use my own
stuff in a completely new environment and the amount of stuff I'm learning
on a daily basis is quite insane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would think using eating your own dogfood results in more active
contributions but it turns out that quite the opposite is happening.  As I
have written about before we're using Werkzeug itself instead of Flask for
it and we went some new and interesting ways in utilizing our stack.  I'm
very proud about what we accomplished in the last half year and it gave me
a few new insights into software architecture which I eventually want to
integrate into my libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However a naive implementation also means breaking compatibility and I am
not very keen on that.  However with Python 3 becoming more and more
interesting I am currently playing with different ideas how to evolve the
libraries in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason is that I have to change my workflow.  The way I was
handling my email inbox over the last few years worked fine for me until
now.  If you sent me a mail in the last two months there is a high chance
I might have missed it.  The truth is that running your own mail server
these days has become a science in itself and I am no longer willing to do
that.  At the same time however I don't want to migrate mails off to a
hosted solution without ensuring I get stuff out of there easily if the
need ever comes up.  As it stands right now I clear out my mailbox in the
morning and at night I have 120 mails in it after filters.  And 90% of
that is what I would classify as various types of spam that my spamfilter
does not assume is spam.  I'm spending too much time currently dealing
with mail and that generally leaves me in a very unhappy state overwards
so that I don't want to deal with my github inbox as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worst part about all that is that it just piles up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, not going to keep it this way but I think I might have to invest
a week into migrating my mail to something else and go over &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the
things that piled up for my projects and make some clear decisions in how
to improve that flow.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Application Mimetypes and Encodings</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/7/19/application-mimetypes-and-encodings</id>
    <updated>2013-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/7/19/application-mimetypes-and-encodings" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For some reason lots of people are under the impression that each and
every mimetype accepts a charset parameter.  If you think that is the
case: that is incorrect.  If a mimetype accepts a charset parameter
depends on the mimetype and as a rule of thumb, mimetypes that don't start
with â€œtext/â€ often don't accept one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two mimetypes where I constantly see people putting charset
declarations next to incorrectly, and then causing a lot of confusion, now
to the point where implementations on the server side discard the actual
specification.  These mimetypes are &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;application/json&lt;/tt&gt; and
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;application/x-www-form-urlencoded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.  Neither of those accept a charset.
(On the other hand &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;application/xml&lt;/tt&gt; for instance accepts a charset).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you specify a charset for those?  You don't!  You don't have to
or you can't and in both cases for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;json-mimetype&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;JSON Mimetype&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JSON mimetype is defined by &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4627&quot;&gt;RFC 4627&lt;/a&gt; and it specifies that the mimetype
does not require any parameters and does not provide any optional
parameters.  About the encoding it has the following to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;literal-block&quot;&gt;
Encoding considerations: 8bit if UTF-8; binary if UTF-16 or UTF-32

   JSON may be represented using UTF-8, UTF-16, or UTF-32.  When JSON
   is written in UTF-8, JSON is 8bit compatible.  When JSON is
   written in UTF-16 or UTF-32, the binary content-transfer-encoding
   must be used.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a little bit up, it also explains how to keep them apart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;literal-block&quot;&gt;
Since the first two characters of a JSON text will always be ASCII
characters [RFC0020], it is possible to determine whether an octet
stream is UTF-8, UTF-16 (BE or LE), or UTF-32 (BE or LE) by looking
at the pattern of nulls in the first four octets.

        00 00 00 xx  UTF-32BE
        00 xx 00 xx  UTF-16BE
        xx 00 00 00  UTF-32LE
        xx 00 xx 00  UTF-16LE
        xx xx xx xx  UTF-8
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, people started sending charset parameters.  And as they
started sending charset parameters, people started accepting those charset
parameters.  The Python requests library for instance will honor the
charset parameter which now makes it possible to send latin1 data to it.
Not just that, it also honors all kinds of BOMs even though they were
never allowed in the mimetype to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't negatively credit requests for that though because it's on the
receiving side and there supporting more than what the standard says is a
common practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;url-encoding-mimetype&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;URL Encoding Mimetype&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;application/x-www-form-urlencoded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; does not support a charset either.
This one for a different reason however.  The reason for this is that
browsers don't really follow HTTP much when it comes to text submission
for legacy reasons.  Browsers will usually not tell the server of which
encoding their data is.  That's usually also not necessary, because the
encoding the browser should use is defined by the server (it's either
defaulting to utf-8 or is defined in the accept-charset parameter of the
form).  Since the server already knows that, the web application will just
know in which encoding it comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However this means that for everything else but the browser and the
application the encoding is unknown!  You cannot reliably determine the
encoding from an HTTP proxy for instance, unless you parse the HTML and
reimplement the browser's charset selection logic and remember it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;application/x-www-form-urlencoded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; does not have a charset,
because the encoding is done on a different level.  It's not decoded from
bytes to unicode as part of HTTP, it's decoded as part of the
application's and only the application has enough information to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTML5 added support for letting you add an empty hidden form tag with the
special name &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;_charset_&lt;/tt&gt; and the browser will fill it with the charset
it used to submit the form, but HTTP proxies and other middleware won't be
able to rely on that unless they know that the application will always
emit that field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in short: &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;application/x-www-form-urlencoded&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; does not allow charset
definitions.  You will have to check with the application to see which
charset it expects.  Chances are, it's going to be utf-8 these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;why-does-it-matter&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why does it Matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It matters because if anything we need to get charsets simplified.  And
there is already a lot of complexity in character set handling we will
always need to do.  Adding a whole new set of confusion by adding charset
parameters to things that previously did not have them should not be done
without at least drafting up a spec about what that means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Appreciating Design</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2012/2/11/appreciating-design</id>
    <updated>2012-02-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2012/2/11/appreciating-design" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think no piece of software had a bigger impact on my work than
&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://trac.edgewall.org/&quot;&gt;Trac&lt;/a&gt;.  Nowadays people often look down on
Trac for various different reasons but if you keep in mind how bug
management and revision control web interfaces in the open source world
looked before Trac you can see why it initially had that much hype around
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;learning-from-trac&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning from Trac&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Trac was released tons of Open Source projects used it.  It had a
slick design and did the few things it provided quite well.  The wiki was
not great but useable, the integrated subversion support was very well
implemented and the bug Tracker was simple but friendly.  It was the first
bug Tracker that I had used that by default could have been presented to a
non technical user without having to tweak it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trac had a reasonable user interface design compared to the competition.
But the beauty of Trac has always been the code that runs it.  For the
German ubuntu community I deployed a phpBB installation a few years prior
to when I used Trac first.  One of the great features of phpBB was that
people wrote extensions for it that provided extra functionality to the
base bulletin board system.  The way these plugins worked however was by
actually modifying the code.  Called â€œmodsâ€ they came with long
installation instructions that showed the specific places where you had to
copy/paste code in.  Not even diff files were provided in those days but
it still sortof worked because people took the time to hand patch their
installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trac on the other hand always had a real plugin system.  The base system
was littered with interfaces and hook points that plugins could utilize to
add extra functionality.  Trac's code taught me proper software and API
design.  Now it seems obvious that this is how you create libraries and
applications but the perfection that Trac had in that regard is still
largely unmatched.  At least in the Python world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance Trac always supported running more than one Trac instance per
Python interpreter.  It was from the ground up designed for that.  Django
as a framework still does not do that.  Which is especially sad
considering that Django is a framework and not an application.  You could
not reimplement Trac in Django without losing this functionality.  Trac
also had the concept of an instance folder where the instance specific
files are dropped (design, static files, uploads, configuration, the
sqlite db if used, per instance plugins etc.) which more people should
consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trac also explicitly did not adopt hyped technologies if they went against
their design principles.  They wanted to use a template engine that was
extensible and built on XML to properly support XHTML (which was hip and
cool at the time) but Kid did not serve that purpose.  It did not scale
properly to the large pages that were generated and it did some funky
things with the Python import systems.  Christopher Lenz wrote Genshi
as a result of that which was a reimplementation of the Kid principles but
with a largely improved implementation.  Genshi is still (from the design
perspective) the coolest piece of template engine you can get in Python
land.  It's also the reason why I no longer hate XML all that much because
properly used it's actually very clever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However all of that is completely irrelevant because Trac and Genshi
failed in other areas.  They were amazingly well written but all that came
at huge costs.  Trac was a memory hog and some early design mistakes that
everybody relied on were only slowly phased out.  For instance before Trac
had Genshi they used a template engine called quicksilver.  It was
implemented in C and used a special syntax similar to JSON to specify the
template context.  When that was replaced with Genshi it broke existing
plugins and provided users with a good excuse to switch from Trac to
alternatives that had the functionality they required built in.  Trac was
also built around the subversion idea of having one huge repository for
everything.  This became a problem when decentralized version control
systems popularized the concept of having more than one repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;users-don-t-care-or-do-they&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Users don't care, or do they?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately all of that would have been great however if the users would
have appreciated the elegance of the design.  But that's not how it seems
to work.  A user expects his software to work and the internals don't
matter at all.  And this is not just true for Trac.  Battlefield 3, which
I &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;/2011/11/15/modern-web-applications-are-here/&quot;&gt;wrote about last year&lt;/a&gt;, moved the main
menu into a browser.  There are a bunch of reasons why the whole concept
in generally is technically amazing, but for the user it was not
understandable why it was cool or useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not that users are dumb and would not understand it, but it was never
communicated in the first place.  I don't know if it's because the
developers did not take their pride far enough in showing everybody how
cool it actually is or if they think users would not understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's compare this to cars for a moment.  If I look around for a car, the
design is only half the reason.  I look for the technical details when I
shell out that much money.  I want to know why it's cool, I was to see
images of the engine and internals.  I want to read about the design ideas
that went into every part of the product.  True, there will be some people
that just want a car, but those are not selling your car anyways.  If a
friend of mine shows up with a brand new BMW I can promise you he will
start telling me about the cool details, he wants me to actually try it
and ultimately he wants me to get this car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple seems to be doing very much the same.  Many Apple computer users
are as loyal to their product as buyers of cars.  They will point how
cool the case design is, how nicely the lid closes, how cute the machine
looks when the sleep light is â€œbreathingâ€ or how few problems they have
with it.  I know many flaws in my Macs but that does not stop me from
continue supporting the company and getting their products.  That's
because I appreciate the work that went into every part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Head over to the Apple website and you see the product in the center like
you see a car.  Apple not only sells you the product there, they also
provide videos of the assembling process.  They let designers share their
thoughts that went into every aspect of the product and they show you that
they love what they created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why don't we do that about software products?  Trac probably would not
have become better by itself just because users would know what goes on
behind the scenes, but I can almost promise you that more developers would
have had a look at the internals if they were communicated properly and
that might have helped improving it.  As it stands right now, only a small
community remains around Trac and only one active developer remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Battlefield 3 it's very similar.  The advert said â€œthe easiest way to
play with friendsâ€ but it did not say why Battlelog (their online
community and also main menu) was cool.  Why it's better for the user than
the main menu being in the game.  Combined with the fact that the game did
not deliver in some other parts (such as missing VOIP support) people
suddenly start blaming battlelog for parts it does not have anything to do
with it.  And an unhappy fanbase is the very last you want to have when it
comes to multiplayer games because those games are sold in a very similar
way: if my friends play I want to play it too.  Selling technical
excellence to computer gamers would not have been hard either because they
take pride in â€œknowing moreâ€ about computers and game then their console
playing friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;make-them-appreciate-it&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make them appreciate it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess to a large degree the idea of â€œthe best design is the one you
don't noticeâ€ plays into that but that does not mean it wouldn't be great
to point it out nonetheless.  And by that I don't mean putting a red arrow
on the product saying â€œthis is a cool design elementâ€ but by providing a
nicely designed website or folder that shows the thought process that went
into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know nothing about cars but damn do I love looking at brochures and
reading about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Battlelog: Modern Web Applications are Here</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2011/11/15/modern-web-applications-are-here</id>
    <updated>2011-11-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2011/11/15/modern-web-applications-are-here" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's the shooter season of the year and this fall was all about Modern
Warfare 3 versus Battlefield 3.  And being the kind of game they are they
also try to keep their audience playing by introducing some additional
level of engagement.  Both Call of Duty and Battlefield introduced their
own online community websites and statistic platforms.  Call of Duty has
Elite, Battlefield has Battlelog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just because these services are sitting in the same spot it does not
mean they are in any way similar.  And that actually goes for more than
just their monetization plans and feature sets.  Elite is a traditional
application as traditional as it can be.  You sign up, there is Flash,
there is a bit of JavaScript, there are tons of requests for each page and
a playercard transmits about 3 MB of data to your client.  Not very
interesting to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what are they doing?  Notwithstanding some of their respective extra
features both Battlelog and Elite are essentially a social network for
shooter games that expose the statistics of your individual gameplay as
well as the one of your friends to you.  Everything you do in the game is
reflected on these websites and you can further interact with the game
there by commenting on gameplay and chatting up with friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elite by itself is not very interesting technology wise, however Battlelog
certainly is.  It shows that an application that is probably used by
millions of gamers can be built on modern web technology as well.  And
under the hood is one of the most interesting ways to built a modern web
application that I think you should check out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;embrace-the-client&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Embrace the Client&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months back I was claiming that WSGI is not the place for pluggable
applications and that it would make sense &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;/2011/7/27/the-pluggable-pipedream/&quot;&gt;to assemble applications on the
client-side&lt;/a&gt;.  Turns out, Battlelog
is doing just that.  While I do not know what all of their infrastructure
looks like, their network graph and license information on the page is
revealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Battlelog is written by a company called &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://esn.me/&quot;&gt;ESN&lt;/a&gt; and their
infrastructure from the released code is basically Python 2.x with
gevent as well as JavaScript with jQuery and their own stuff on the client
and Java for their websocket backend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you send an HTTP request to the website it appears to work as if it was
a regular website.  You get a bunch of HTML rendered and nothing
interesting happens.  However if you click on any link you do not get HTML
transmitted.  Instead what is transmitted is JSON, the HTML5 history API
is used to modify the URL dynamically and all the HTML is rendered on the
client.  Since it appears to be able to do both we can compare the sizes
of the data transmitted easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HTML for the index page is 18KB in size.  If we trigger the request to
the same URL with just the JSON it's 4KB.  Not only is it less to
transmit, it also means that the server is essentially just generating
JSON instead of rendering whole templates which also means a performance
improvement for the client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The platform is a work of beauty in general and I am amazed how little I
have heard on the interwebs about it.  So to give you an idea why it's an
incredible technical achievement on so many levels, here the breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;feature-overview&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feature Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand what Battlelog is here a brief overview of what it does.
These are not necessarily the features that are immediately obvious to the
user but are very obvious for the interested developer that wants to peak
under the hood:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the website insta-updates based on information coming from the push
connection.  If you have the website open in the background you can
hear a notification sound being played just the second your game ends.
That notification sound is for the report generated from the round you
played.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The same websocket connection for the website is also used for the
chat feature on the site as well as game invites and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the pages can be rendered on both the client side via JavaScript
as well as the server.  How this work I cannot tell you but I find it
interesting considering the server side is Python.  So their templates
compile to Python and JavaScript as it seems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Battlelog comes with an optional browser plugin that makes it possible
to join into a game on the PC version of Battlefield right from within
the browser.  This plugin can interact with the game and exposes some
other functionality that is lacking in HTML5 (such as issuing pings).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;how-the-client-operates&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How the Client Operates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to understand why Battlelog is interesting engineering we have to
reconstruct what it appears to be doing.  Again, I am not claiming
knowledge of their server technology, I basically just observed what I saw
and concluded a few things from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you access a page you get some nicely rendered HTML back.  One of the
things that is also transmitted to you is a large JavaScript document that
contains their client side framework as well as the rendering instructions
for all pages compiled to JavaScript code.  The framework then hooks into
your browser's navigation code an intercepts all page loads.  Instead of
letting the browser replace the page with something new on load it instead
does the HTTP request via Ajax and adds an additional header to the HTTP
request: &lt;cite&gt;X-Ajax-Navigation&lt;/cite&gt;.  If the server side sees that header it will
instead of rendering to HTML deliver the data that is normally passed to
the template as JSON.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data you get back is everything the page needs to render, including
the name of the template.  When that data arrives on the client the
browser replaces the current page content with the data that was rendered
on the client side from the received JSON.  Not only that, it also makes
sure to use the HTML5 history API to change the browser URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user does not notice that anything interesting is going on unless he's
tech savvy enough to open the firebug network panel and watch the system
operate.  In fact the whole thing is so incredible smooth that you would
not notice anything interesting besides the fact that the page loads fast.
I mean seriously fast.  Clicking on a link in Battlelog is such a snappy
operation it's haunting for the trained web developer eye.  Very few
systems respond this quickly.  This is especially noticeable on pages that
do not involve a lot of different data such as the news section of the
website or the forums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the website it also has a bar on the bottom of the screen
that shows notifications, your friendlist, open chat windows and a few
other things.  This bar can have state.  You can toggle windows open and
closed, you can scroll in the chat window, enter new next and the bar will
stay open and unchanged if you navigate to a different page.  True, this
is nothing special these days, facebook does it too.  However from the
design that Battlelog follows this comes natural.  When the page contents
are hooked in the DOM element for that bar on the bottom is preserved and
not touched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other aspect of Battlelog is the real time component with web sockets.
I have not looked too far into that but it appears that it's based on an
abstraction layer on top of web sockets, Flash or whatever is supported
that was written by ESN for other projects in mind as well.  The server
code sends an information to the push hub which handles the socket
connection for the clients.  This way various systems can inform the
client about updates, that does not even have to be Battlelog itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;why-the-client&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why the Client?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it's not necessarily the case with Battlelog, there are a bunch of
really good reasons why you want to render stuff on the client side:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can do partial updates.  And you want partial updates since they
are good for the user experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can mix content together from different resources which is good
for caching.  If there is information on the page that rarely changes
and is the same for each user you can load it from a well cached page
and keep it in the client's DOM and never replace it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generating HTML on the server side is more expensive than on the
client.  You don't pay for the client side and even the fastest
template engine on the server is beaten by an optimized JSON
serializer.  Faster apps mean more satisfied customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you do not have a JavaScript heavy application, moving
computations to the client side is a good thing.  This obviously assumes
that it does not break the navigation like some websites do.  Battlelog
does not do that.  The principles on which Battlelog is built would also
very well work in a more traditional application.  However it requires a
well structured architecture were the data you're sending to the template
engine is simple (and secure!) enough that you can put it in JSON and that
the templates themselves are simple enough that compiling them to
JavaScript is an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jinja2 for instance could in theory execute on the client but practically
not.  Practically it's exposing a little bit too much of Python to make
sense to compile to JavaScript.  But a template language much like Jinja2
could be written that would make this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I think you could build a microframework that would very well
support this paradigm and still be agnostic to the JavaScript code you're
running on the client for the most part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-native-code-thing&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Native Code Thing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real interesting thing about Battlelog however is a Windows PC
specific component.  If you are heading to Battlelog from a Windows PC and
you own the PC version of Battlefield 3 you can launch into a game right
from within the browser.  How does this work?  It works with the help of a
browser plugin that exposes additional functionality to the in browser
client.  Namely it has a function to start the game and pass it
information as well as a general purpose function to ping an IP address
which is used for the server browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact if you are playing on PC this is how the game is launched, always.
There is no in game menu, you join from within your browser.  This is mind
blowing thing.  First of all it makes it easier for DICE to update the
server infrastructure since it's now mostly separated from the client and
also makes for much quicker iterations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The communication for the most part works in one-way but in a cycle as it
seems.  If you log into Battlelog and head to the server browser you get a
list of servers.  How does &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; work?  Here's how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you send an HTTP request to Battlelog it determines your
approximate location based on the request IP.  This way it can
pre-filter servers for you that are probably near you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each server connects to a ping site on connect.  There are a couple
different ping sites for different countries.  The USA have three I
think, Europe has one, Japan has one, Australia etc.  Each ping site
then notifies Battlelog about the distance of that server to the ping
site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on that information as well as your filter settings, Battlelog
now sends you a list of servers.  Once that data is retrieved by the
client it starts connecting to the browser plugin and asks it to ping
all the server IPs it received.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you now want to join that server it sends an HTTP request to
the Battlelog server side to reserve a slot on that server.  In
response it gets a token that identifies that slot.  When the server
managed to reserve a slot for that player the client uses the
serverlog plugin to boot up the game.  It passes that token to the
game alongside a secret and lets the game boot in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While the game is booting up it uses the received authentication
information to use the slot that was reserved.  When it loaded up
properly it notifies the Battlelog client with the help of the plugin
about changes in the executable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The plugin also exposes some more functionality of the client to the
website which makes it possible for the JavaScript part of Battlelog
to close the game away and initiate some other game modes such as coop
hosting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;thinking-does-it-need-the-plugin&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thinking: Does it need the Plugin?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now here was me thinking.  Would the plugin be necessary to accomplish all
of the above things or could it be done in a different way?  Native
applications are here to stay, that's a given.  However more and more
stuff of what a native application does can be moved into a browser for
great success.  So how does a web application speak to a native
application?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional way is by letting the application register a custom URL
scheme and then letting the user click on that link which then launches
the application.  That's unfortunately a one way communication only.  But
that might be everything that is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is how it could be done.  Battlefield or any other application
that wants to do the same but without the browser plugin could instead
register a URL handler with a unique name.  Let's say &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;battlefield3://&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.
The operating system then knows about this URL scheme and can start a
handling application.  What can we do with this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server component would have to uniquely identify a user for starters.
Considering that each user has to log in that's fine anyways.  Then next
to that user information one would have to remember if the game is
running and how.  What does that mean?  Let's start with the simple case:
the game is not running.  The Battlelog server looks at the current user
and sees he or she does not have the game running.  Consequently it will
generate a unique token and generate a URL to the URL scheme (for instance
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;battlefield3://start?token=...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.  It then generates a JavaScript prompt
that informs the user that he has to launch the game by clicking on the
link generated.  This is the only chance in flow that is necessary.  By
clicking that link the user agrees that he wants to start that
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But instead of launching the game it starts a daemon.  That daemon takes
the token and picks a random TCP port on the system and starts an HTTP
server there.  Once that server is running it notifies the central server
that it's running and on what port.  Since the web browser has a push
notification channel open it will get a notification now that the daemon
is running and on which port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that it can use HTTP and JSONP to communicate with the daemon.  But
how does the daemon know when to shut down?  Basically that daemon will
needs to be informed when to shut down.  I would assume that 15 minutes
without a ping from the browser would be a good indication that it should
destruct itself.  When shutting down it also tells Battlelog that it's no
longer running to clear out the port entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally to make this better it should not only record the port but
also an identifier that uniquely identifies the machine the daemon is
running on so that the user can alternate between different computers
without ending up with weird behavior where the central server is
informing the browser that the game is running when in fact it's running
on a different machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Battlefield 3 supports only one running game per user account it
does not make sense to support more than one session.  If that would be
wanted it could obviously be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside here obviously is that it needs a websocket connection and a
central server that acts as mediator between the different systems
(daemon, client side app).  In Battlefield 3's case that would not be a
concern (and already is not) since it's an online game.  The second
problem here is that it needs one additional user interaction: the user
has to click on the link to activate it.  This currently is not necessary
in Battlelog since it's provided by a plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;browser-native-code-communication&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Browser &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; Native Code Communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole concept of using a browser application as a frontend for a
native application is an interesting thing indeed.  Due to offline support
becoming widespread that is also no longer a concern if the application
can largely run in the client side.  But that would break my above
hypothetical example of interacting with a local application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Falling back to a browser plugin currently is the only way to make a
consenting communication with a local application.  I really wonder if
there is not room for improvement by having an API in HTML5 that makes
this possible which would also work for offline applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically what would be needed is a simple way for a two way communication
with a local application.  That application would have to register itself
somewhere and then be able to respond to the client's requests.  It could
totally work like a CGI script (eg: speak HTTP via stdin/stdout).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there is a lot of potential for such applications in the future
and Battlelog shows that it can be done already with a little help of a
small plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;killer-applications&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Killer Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last thing.  Battlefield 3 sold a couple millions of copies.  The PC
users all have to update to recent version of their browsers since the
website basically demands a modern browser.  Even with all the fallbacks
in place, it kinda forces people to update.  For a certain audience
websites like Battlelog can be the killer application of modern HTML5
features.  Keep this in mind.  In case you have a similar audience that's
something to take advantage of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Be Careful About What You Dislike</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/11/5/be-careful-about-what-you-dislike</id>
    <updated>2016-11-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/11/5/be-careful-about-what-you-dislike" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last few months I keep making the same observation over and over again
in various different contexts: that whenever you are confronted with a
very strong opinion about a topic, reasonable discussions about the topic
often involve arguments that have long become outdated or are no longer
strictly relevant to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I mean by that is that given a controversial topic, a valid argument
for one side of the other is being repeated by a crowd of people that once
heard it, even after that argument stops being valid.  This happens because
often the general situation changed and the argument references a reality
that no longer exists in the same form.  Instead of reevaluating the
environment however, goalposts are moved to restore the general sentiment
of the opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you a practical example of this problem I can just go by a topic I
have a very strong opinion about: Python 3.  When Python 3 was not a huge
thing yet I started having conversations with people in the community
about the problems I see with splitting the community and complexity of
porting.  Not just that, I also kept bringing up general questions about
some of the text and byte decisions.  I started doing talks about the
topic and write blog articles that kept being shared.  Nowadays when I go
to a conference I very quickly end up in conversations where other
developers come to me and see me as the &amp;quot;Does not like Python 3 guy&amp;quot;.
While I still am not a friend of some of the decisions in Python 3 I am
very much aware that Python 3 in 2016 is a very different Python 3 than 6
years ago or earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I myself campaigned for some changes to Python 3 that made it
possible to achieve better ports (like the reintroduction of the &lt;cite&gt;u&lt;/cite&gt;
prefix on Unicode string literals) and the bulk of my libraries work on
Python 3 for many years now.  It's a fact that in 2016 the problems that
people have with Python 3 are different than they used to have before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to very interesting conversations where I can have a highly
technical conversation about a very specific issue with Python 3 and
thoughts about how to do it differently or deal with it (like some of the
less obvious consequences of the new text storage model) and another
person joins into the conversation with an argument against Python 3 that
has long stropped being valid.  Why?  Because there is a cost towards
porting to Python 3 and a chance is not seen.  This means that a person
with a general negativity towards Python 3 would seek me out and try to
reaffirm their opposition to a port to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same thing is happening with JavaScript where there is a general negative
sentiment about programming in it but not everybody is having good
arguments for it.  There are some that actually program a lot in it and
dislike specific things about the current state of the ecosystem, but
generally acknowledge that the language is evolving, and then there are
those that take advantage of unhappiness and bring their heavily outdated
opposition against JavaScript into a conversation just to reaffirm their
own opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is hardly confined to the programming world.  I made the same
discovery about CETA.  CETA is a free trade agreement between the European
Union and Canada and it had the misfortune of being negotiated at the same
time as the more controversial TTIP with the US.  The story goes roughly
like this: TTIP was negotiated in secrecy (as all trade agreements are)
and there were strong disagreements between what the EU and what the US
thought trade should look like.  Those differences were about food safety
standards and other highly sensitive topics.  Various organizations on
both the left and right extremes of the political scale started to grab
any remotely controversial information that leaked out to shift the public
opinion towards negativity to TTIP.  Then the entire thing spiraled out of
control: people not only railed against TTIP but took their opposition
and looked for similar contracts and found CETA.  Since both are trade
agreements there is naturally a lot of common ground between them.  The
subtleties where quickly lost.  Where the initial arguments against TTIP
were food standards, public services and intransparent ISDS courts many of
the critics failed to realize that CETA fundamentally was a different
beast.  Not only was it already a much improved agreement from the start,
but it kept being modified from the initial public version of it to the
one that was finally sent to national parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However despite what I would have expected: that critics go in and
acknowledge that their criticism was being heard instead slowly moved the
goalposts.  At this point there is so much emotion and misinformation in
the general community that the goalpost moved all the way to not
supporting further free trade at all.  In the general conversation about
ISDS and standards many people brought introduced their own opinions about
free trade and their dislike towards corporations and multinationals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This I assume is human behavior.  Admitting that you might be wrong is
hard enough, but it's even harder when you had validation that you were
right in the past.  In particular that an argument against something might
no longer be valid because that something has changed in the meantime is
hard.  I'm not sure what the solution to this is but I definitely realized
in the few years on my own behavior that one needs to be more careful
about stating strong opinions in public.  At the same time however I think
we should all be more careful dispelling misinformation in conversations
even if the general mood supports your opinion.  As an example while
emotionally I like hearing stories about how JavaScript's packaging causes
pain to developers since I experienced it first hand, I know from a
rational point of view that the ecosystem is improving a tremendous
speeds.  Yes I have been burned by npm but it's not like this is not
tremendously improving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that has been put to paper once is hard to remove from people's
minds.  In particular in the technological context technology moves so
fast that very likely something you read once might no longer be up to
date as little as six months later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I suppose my proposal to readers is not to fall into that trap and to
assume that the environment around oneself keeps on changing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Beautiful Native Libraries</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/8/18/beautiful-native-libraries</id>
    <updated>2013-08-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/8/18/beautiful-native-libraries" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm obsessed with nice APIs.  Not just APIs however, also in making the
overall experience of using a library as good as possible.  For Python
there are quite a few best practices around by now but it feels like there
is not really a lot of information available about how to properly
structure a native library.  What do I mean by native library?
Essentially a dylib/DLL/so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I'm currently spending more time on C and C++ than Python at work I
figured I might take the opportunity and collect my thoughts on how to
write proper shared libraries that do not annoy your users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;shared-or-static&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shared or Static?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post almost entirely assumes that you are building a DLL or shared
library and not something you link statically.  While it sounds like a
statically and dynamically linked library are essentially the same thing
where the only difference is how you link against it, there is much more
to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a dynamically linked library you have much better control over your
symbols.  Dynamically linked libraries also work much better between
different programming languages.  Nothing stops you from writing a library
in C++ and then using it in Python.  In fact, that's exactly how I
recommend doing unittests against such libraries.  More about that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;which-language&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Which Language?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you want to write a library that compiles into a DLL or something of
that sort and it should be somewhat platform independent.  Which languages
can you actually use there?  Right now you can pick between C and C++ and
soon you might also be able to add Rust to that list.  Why not others?  C
is easy: because that's the only language that actually defines a somewhat
stable ABI.  Strictly speaking it's not the language that defines it, it's
the operating system, but in one way or another, C is the language of
choice for libraries and the C calling conventions is the lingua franca of
shared libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;â€œThe greatest trick that C ever pulled was convince the world that it does
not have a runtimeâ€.  I'm not sure where I heard the quote first, but it's
incredibly appropriate when talking about libraries.  Essentially C is so
commonplace that everything can assume that some basic functionality is
provided by the C standard library.  That's the one thing that everybody
agreed on that exists.  For C++ the situation is more complicated.  C++
needs a bunch of extra functionality that is not provided by the C
standard library.  Primarily it needs support for exception handling.  C++
however degrades otherwise nicely to C calling conventions so it's very
easy to still write libraries in it, that completely hide the fact that
there is C++ behind the scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other languages that's not so easy however.  Why for instance is it
not a good idea to write a library in Go?  The reason for this is that Go
for needs quite a heavy runtime that does garbage collection and provides
a scheduler for it's coroutines.  Rust is getting closer to not having any
runtime requirements besides the C standard library which will make it
possible to write libraries in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now however, C++ is most likely the language you want to use.  Why
not C?  The reason for this is that Microsoft's C compiler is notoriously
bad at receiving language updates and you would otherwise be stuck with
C89.  Obviously you could just use a different compiler on Windows but
that causes a whole bunch of problems for the users of your library if
they want to compile it themselves.  Requiring a tool chain that is not
native to the operating system is an easy way to alienate your developer
audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would however generally recommend to a very C like subset of C++: don't
use exceptions, don't use RTTI, don't build crazy constructors.  The rest
of the post assumes that C++ is indeed the language of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;public-headers&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Public Headers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The library you're building should ideally have exactly one public header
file.  Internally go nuts and create as many headers as you want.  You
want that one public header file to exist, even if you think your library
is only ever going to be linked against something that is not C.  For
instance Python's CFFI library can parse header files and build bindings
out of that.  People of all languages know how headers work, they will
have a look at them to build their own bindings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What rules are there to follow in headers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;header-guards&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Header Guards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each public header that other people use should have sufficiently unique
header guards to make sure they can be included multiple times safely.
Don't get too creative with the guards, but also don't be too generic with
them.  It's no fun including a header that has a super generic include
guard at the top (like &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;UTILS_H&lt;/tt&gt; and nothing else).  You also want to
make sure that there are &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;extern &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&lt;/tt&gt; markers for C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be your minimal header:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#ifndef YOURLIB_H_INCLUDED&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define YOURLIB_H_INCLUDED&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#ifdef __cplusplus&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;extern&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#endif&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/* code goes here */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#ifdef __cplusplus&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;export-markers&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Export Markers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you yourself will probably include your header file as well you
will need to make sure that there are macros defined that export your
functions.  This is necessary on Windows and it's a really good idea on
other platforms as well.  Essentially it can be used to change the
visibility of symbols.  I will go into that later, for the time being just
add something that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#ifndef YL_API&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#  ifdef _WIN32&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     if defined(YL_BUILD_SHARED) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/* build dll */&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#         define YL_API __declspec(dllexport)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     elif !defined(YL_BUILD_STATIC) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/* use dll */&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#         define YL_API __declspec(dllimport)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     else &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/* static library */&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#         define YL_API&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#  else&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     if __GNUC__ &amp;gt;= 4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#         define YL_API __attribute__((visibility(&amp;quot;default&amp;quot;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     else&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#         define YL_API&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#     endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#  endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#endif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows it will set &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/tt&gt; (I used &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;YL&lt;/tt&gt; as short version for
â€œYour Libraryâ€ here, pick a prefix that fits you) for DLLs appropriately
depending on what flag is set.  Whoever includes the header without doing
anything fancy before will automatically get &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;__declspec(dllimport)&lt;/tt&gt; in
its place.  This is a really good default behavior on Windows.  For other
platforms nothing is set unless a somewhat recent GCC/clang version is
used in which case the default visibility marker is added.  As you can see
some macros can be defined to change which branch is taken.  For instance
when you build the library you would tell the compiler to also defined
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;YL_BUILD_SHARED&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows the default behavior for DLLs has always been: all symbols are
not exported default unless marked with &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;__declspec(dllexport)&lt;/tt&gt;.  On
other platforms unfortunately the behavior has always been to export
everything.  There are multiple ways to fix that, one is the visibility
control of GCC 4.  This works okay, but there are some extra things that
need to be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that the in-source visibility control is not the silver
bullet.  For a start the marker will do nothing unless the library is
compiled with &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;-fvisibility=hidden&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.  More important than that however
is that this will only affect your own library.  If you statically link
anything against your library, that library might expose symbols you do
not want to expose.  Imagine for instance you write a library that depends
on another library you want to statically link in.  This library's symbols
will also be exported from your library unless you prevent that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works differently on different platforms.  On Linux you can pass
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;--exclude-libs&lt;/span&gt; ALL&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;ld&lt;/tt&gt; and the linker will remove those symbols
automatically.  On OS X it's tricker because there is no such
functionality in the linker.  The easiest solution is to have a common
prefix for all functions.  For instance if all your functions start with
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;yl_&lt;/tt&gt; it's easy to tell the linker to hide everything else.  You do this
by creating a symbols file and then pointing the linker to it with
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;-exported_symbols_list&lt;/span&gt; symbols.txt&lt;/tt&gt;.  The contents of this file can be
the single line &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;_yl_*&lt;/tt&gt;.  Windows we can ignore as DLLs need explicit
export markers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;careful-with-includes-and-defines&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Careful with Includes and Defines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to be careful about is that your headers should not include
too many things.  Generally I believe it's fine for a header to include
things like &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;stdint.h&lt;/tt&gt; to get some common integer types.  However what
you should not do is being clever and defining types yourself.  For
instance msgpack had the brilliant idea to define &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;int32_t&lt;/tt&gt; and a few
other types for Visual Studio 2008 because it lacks the &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;stdint.h&lt;/tt&gt;
header.  This is problematic as only one library can define those types
then.  Instead the better solution is to ask the user to provide a
replacement &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;stdint.h&lt;/tt&gt; header for older Visual Studio versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially do not ever include &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;windows.h&lt;/tt&gt; in a library header.  That
header pulls in so much stuff that Microsoft added extra defines to make
it leaner (&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;WINDOWS_LEAN_AND_MEAN&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;WINDOWS_EXTRA_LEAN&lt;/tt&gt; and
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;NOMINMAX&lt;/tt&gt;).  If you need &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;windows.h&lt;/tt&gt; included, have a private header
file that's only included for your &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;.cpp&lt;/tt&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;stable-abi&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stable ABI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not put any structs into public headers unless you are 100% sure that
you will never change them.  If you do want to expose structs and you do
want to add extra members later, make sure that the user does not have to
allocate that header.  If the user does have to allocate that header, add
a version or size information as first member into the struct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft generally puts the size of structs into the structs to allow
adding members later, but this leads to APIs that are just not fun to use.
If you can try to avoid having too many structs in the headers, if you
can't at least try to come up with alternative methods to make the API
suck less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With structs you also run into the issue that alignments might differ
between different compilers.  Unfortunately there are cases where you are
dealing with a project that forces the alignment to be different for the
whole project and that will obviously also affect the structs in your
header file.  The fewer structs the better :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that should go without saying: do not make macros part of your
API.  A macro is not a symbol and users of languages not based on C will
hate you for having macros there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more note on the ABI stability: it's a very good idea to include
the version of the library both in the header as well as compiled into
the binary.  That way you can easily verify that the header matches the
binary which can save you lots of headaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something like this in the header:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define YL_VERSION_MAJOR 1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define YL_VERSION_MINOR 0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define YL_VERSION ((YL_VERSION_MAJOR &amp;lt;&amp;lt; 16) | YL_VERSION_MINOR)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_get_version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_is_compatible_dll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this in the implementation file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_get_version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_VERSION&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_is_compatible_dll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;unsigned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;major&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_get_version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;major&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_VERSION_MAJOR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;exporting-a-c-api&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exporting a C API&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When exposing a C++ API to C there is not much that needs to be
considered.  Generally for each internal class you have, you would have an
external opaque struct without any fields.  Then provide functions that
call into your internal functions.  Picture a class like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yourlibrary&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;is_pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;tick&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;result_string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internal C++ API is quite obvious, but how do you expose that via C?
Because the external ABI now no longer knows how large the structs are you
will need to allocate memory for the external caller or give it a method
to figure out how much memory to allocate.  I generally prefer to allocate
for the external user and provide a free function as well.  For how to
make the memory allocation system still flexible, have a look at the next
part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now this is the external header (this has to be in &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;extern &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;&lt;/tt&gt;
braces):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_is_pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_tick&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_get_result_string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is how the shim layer would look like in the implementation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define AS_TYPE(Type, Obj) reinterpret_cast&amp;lt;Type *&amp;gt;(Obj)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define AS_CTYPE(Type, Obj) reinterpret_cast&amp;lt;const Type *&amp;gt;(Obj)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AS_TYPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yourlibrary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AS_TYPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yourlibrary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_is_pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AS_CTYPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yourlibrary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;is_pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_tick&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AS_TYPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yourlibrary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tick&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_task_get_result_string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;AS_CTYPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yourlibrary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;result_string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how the constructor and destructor is fully wrapped.  Now there is
one problem with standard C++: it raises exceptions.  Because constructors
have no return value to signal to the outside that something went wrong it
will raise exceptions if the allocation fails.  That's however not the
only problem.  How do we customize how the library allocates memory now?
C++ is pretty ugly in that regard.  But it's largely fixable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we go on: please under no circumstances, make a library, that
pollutes the namespace with generic names.  Always put a common prefix
before all your symbols (like &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;yl_&lt;/tt&gt;) to lower the risk of namespace
clashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;context-objects&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Context Objects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global state is terrible, so what's the solution?  Generally the solution
is to have what I would call â€œcontextâ€ objects that hold the state
instead.  These objects would have all the important stuff on that you
would otherwise put into a global variable.  That way the user of your
library can have multiple of those.  Then make each API function take that
context as first parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially useful if your library is not threadsafe.  That way you
can have one per thread at least, which might already be enough to get
some parallelism out of your code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally each of those context objects could also use a different
allocator, but given the complexities of doing that in C++ I would not be
super disappointed if you did not make that work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;memory-allocation-customization&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Memory Allocation Customization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, constructors can fail and we want to customize memory
allocations, so how do we do this?  In C++ there are two systems
responsible for memory allocations: the allocation operators &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;operator
new&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;operator new[]&lt;/tt&gt; as well as the allocators for containers.  If
you want to customize the allocator you will need to deal with both.
First you need a way to let others override the allocator functions.  The
simplest is to provide something like this in the public header:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_set_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
                              &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
                              &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_calloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_strdup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then in your internal header you can add a bunch of inline functions
that redirect to the function pointers set to an internal struct.  Because
we do not let users provide &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;calloc&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;strdup&lt;/tt&gt; you probably also
want to reimplement those functions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_allocators_s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;extern&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_allocators_s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_calloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;memset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ptr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kr&quot;&gt;inline&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_strdup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;strlen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;memcpy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;length&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the setting of the allocators themselves you probably want to put that
into a separate source file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_allocators_s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;free&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;yl_set_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_realloc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_realloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_yl_allocators&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_free&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;memory-allocators-and-c&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Memory Allocators and C++&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have those functions set, how do we make C++ use them?  This
part is tricky and annoying.  To get your custom classes allocated through
your &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;yl_malloc&lt;/tt&gt; you need to implement the allocation operators in all
your classes.  Because that's quite a repetitive process I recommend
writing a macro for it that can be placed in the private section of the
class.  I chose to pick by convention that it has to go into private, even
though the function it implements are public.  Primarily I did that so
that it lives close to where the data is defined, which in my case is
usually private.  You will need to make sure you don't forget adding that
macro to all your classes private sections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#define YL_IMPLEMENTS_ALLOCATORS \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;public: \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void *operator new(size_t size) { return yl_malloc(size); } \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void operator delete(void *ptr) { yl_free(ptr); } \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void *operator new[](size_t size) { return yl_malloc(size); } \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void operator delete[](void *ptr) { yl_free(ptr); } \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void *operator new(size_t, void *ptr) { return ptr; } \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void operator delete(void *, void *) {} \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void *operator new[](size_t, void *ptr) { return ptr; } \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;    void operator delete[](void *, void *) {} \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;private:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how an example usage would look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;YL_IMPLEMENTS_ALLOCATORS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now with that all &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; classes will be allocated through your allocator
functions.  But what if you want to use STL containers?  Those containers
will not be allocated through your functions yet.  To fix that particular
issue you need to write an STL proxy allocator.  That's an enormously
annoying process because of how complex the interface is, for essentially
doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;cpf&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;limits&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;template&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;ptrdiff_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;difference_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;const_pointer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reference&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;const_reference&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;template&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;U&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rebind&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;U&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;other&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;template&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;U&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;U&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reference&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;const_pointer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;const_reference&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;allocate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size_type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;reinterpret_cast&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;sizeof&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;deallocate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size_type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;size_type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max_size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;numeric_limits&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;sizeof&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;construct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;reinterpret_cast&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;destroy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;operator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;other&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;bool&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;operator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;other&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So before we go on, how does one use this abomination?  Like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;cpf&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;deque&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;cpf&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;deque&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;TaskQueue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;typedef&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;basic_string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;char_traits&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                          &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;proxy_allocator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;char&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would recommend making a header somewhere that defines all the
containers you want to use and then force yourself not to use anything
else from the STL without typedefing it to use the right allocator.
Careful: do not &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;new TaskQueue()&lt;/tt&gt; those things as you would invoke the
global new operator.  Place them instead as members in your own structs so
that the allocation happens as part of your object which has a custom
allocator.  Alternatively just put them on the stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;memory-allocation-failures&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Memory Allocation Failures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind the best way to deal with memory allocation failures is to not
deal with them.  Just don't cause any allocation to fail.  For a library
that's easy to accomplish, just be aware of how much memory you will
allocate in the worst case scenario and if you are unbounded, provide the
user of the library with a way to get an idea of how bad things are.  The
reason for this is that nobody deals with allocation failures either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a start the STL entirely depends on &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;std::bad_alloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; being thrown
from operator new (which we're not doing above, hehe) and will just bubble
up the error for you to deal with it.  When you compile your library
without exception handling then the library will just terminate the
process.  That's pretty terrible, but that's what's going to happen
anyways if you're not careful.  I have seen more code that ignores the
return value of malloc than code that deals with it properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from that: on some systems malloc will totally lie to you about how
much memory is available anyways.  Linux will gladly give you pointers to
memory it can't back up with real physical memory.  This fiat memory
behavior is quite useful but also will mean that you generally already
have to assume that allocation failure might not happen.  So instead of
reporting allocation errors, if you use C++ and you also want to stick to
the STL, then give up on that and just don't run out of memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In computer games the general concept there is to give subsystems their
own allocator and just make sure they never allocate more than what they
are given.  EA seems to recommend the allocator to handle allocation
failures.  For instance when it fails to load more memory it would check
if it can free up some resources that are not needed (like caches) instead
of letting the caller know there is a memory failure.  This works even
with the limited design that the C++ standard gives with allocators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;building&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have written the code, how do you build your library without
making your users unhappy?  If you're like me you come from a Unix
background where makefiles are what builds software.  However that's not
what everybody wants.  Autotools/autoconf are terrible, terrible pieces of
software and if you give that to a windows guy they will call you all
kinds of names.  Instead make sure there are Visual Studio solutions
sitting around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you don't want to deal with Visual Studio because it's not your
toolchain of choice?  What if you want to keep solutions and makefiles in
sync?  The answer to that question is &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://industriousone.com/premake&quot;&gt;premake&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.cmake.org/&quot;&gt;cmake&lt;/a&gt;.  Which of the two you use depends largely on
you.  Both can generate Makefiles, XCode or Visual Studio solutions out of
a simple definition script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to be a huge fan of cmake but I now switched to premake.  The
reason for this is that cmake has some stuff hardcoded which I need to
customize (for instance building a Visual Studio solution for Xbox 360 is
something you cannot do with stock cmake).  Premake has many of the same
problems as cmake but it's written almost entirely in lua and can be
easily customized.  Premake is essentially one executable that includes a
lua interpreter and a bunch of lua scripts.  It's easy to recompile and if
you don't want to, your premake file can override everything if you just
know how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;testing&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly: how do you test your library?  Now obviously there are tons of
testing tools written in C and C++ you can use, but I think the best tools
are actually somewhere else.  Shared libraries are not just for C and C++
to enjoy, you can use them in a variety of languages.  What better way is
there to test your API by using it from a language that is not C++?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case I am using Python to test my libraries.  More to the point: I'm
using &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://pytest.org/&quot;&gt;py.test&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://cffi.readthedocs.org/&quot;&gt;CFFI&lt;/a&gt; to test my library.  This has a couple
of big advantages over directly doing it in C/C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest advantage is the increased iteration speed.  I do not have to
compile my tests at all, they just run.  Not only does the compilation
step fall away, I can also take advantage of Python's dynamic typing and
py.test's good assert statement.  I write myself helpers to print out
information and to convert data between my library and Python and I get
all the benefit of good error reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second advantage is good isolation.  &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pytest-xdist&quot;&gt;pytest-xdist&lt;/a&gt; is a plugin for py.test
that adds the &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pre&quot;&gt;--boxed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; flag to py.test which runs each test in a
separate process.  That's amazingly useful if you have tests that might
crash due to a segfault.  If you enable coredumps on your system you can
then afterwards load up the segfault in gdb and figure out what's wrong.
This also works really well because you don't need to deal with memory
leaks that happen because an assertion failed and the code skips the
cleanup.  The OS will clean up for each test separately.  Unfortunately
that's implemented through the &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;fork()&lt;/tt&gt; system call so it does not work
well on windows right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you use your library with CFFI?  You will need to do two things:
you need to make sure your public header file does not include any other
headers.  If you can't do that, just add a define that disables the
includes (like &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;YL_NOINCLUDE&lt;/tt&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all that's needed to make CFFI work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;cffi&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;FFI&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;here&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;abspath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dirname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;vm&quot;&gt;__file__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;join&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;include&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;yourlibrary.h&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ffi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cdef&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Popen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;([&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;cc&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;-E&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;-DYL_API=&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;-DYL_NOINCLUDE&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;header&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;stdout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PIPE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;communicate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ffi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dlopen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;join&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;build&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;libyourlibrary.dylib&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Place it in a file called &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;testhelpers.py&lt;/tt&gt; next to your tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now obviously that is the simple version that only works on OS X but it's
simple to extend for different operating systems.  In essence this
invokes the C preprocessor and adds some extra defines, then feeds the
return value of that to the CFFI parser.  Afterwards you have a beautiful
wrapped library to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here an example of how such a test could look like.  Just place it in a
file called &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;test_something.py&lt;/tt&gt; and let &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;py.test&lt;/tt&gt; execute it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;testhelpers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ffi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;test_basic_functionality&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_is_pending&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_process&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sleep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.001&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_get_result_string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;assert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ffi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;py.test has other advantages too.  For instance it supports fixtures which
allow you to set up common resources that can be reused between tests.
This is super useful for instance, if using your library requires creating
some sort of context object, setting up common configuration on it, and
later destroying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, just create a &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;conftest.py&lt;/tt&gt; file with the following content:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pytest&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;testhelpers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ffi&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nd&quot;&gt;@pytest.fixture&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;scope&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;function&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;request&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_context_new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_context_set_api_key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;my api key&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_context_set_debug_mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cleanup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_context_free&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;request&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;addfinalizer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cleanup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ctx&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use this now, all you need to do is to add a parameter called
&lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;context&lt;/tt&gt; to your test function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;testhelpers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ffi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;test_basic_functionality&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;task&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;yl_task_new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is longer than usual, here a quick summary of the most
important things to keep in mind when building a native shared library:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write it in C or C++, don't get crazy with building it in a language
that pulls in a whole runtime that takes up CPU and memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No global state if you can avoid it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not define common types in your public headers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not include crazy headers like &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;windows.h&lt;/tt&gt; in your public
headers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be light on includes in your headers altogether.  Consider adding a
way to disable all includes through a define.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take good care about your namespace.  Don't expose symbols you do not
want to be exposed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a macro like &lt;tt class=&quot;docutils literal&quot;&gt;YL_API&lt;/tt&gt; that prefixes each symbol you want to
expose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to build a stable ABI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't go crazy with structs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let people customize the memory allocators.  If you can't do it per
â€œcontextâ€ object, at least do it per library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be careful when using the STL, always only through a typedef that adds
your allocator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't force your users to use your favourite build tool, always make
sure that the user of a library finds a Visual Studio solution and
makefile in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it!  Happy library building!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

