<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Armin Ronacher's Thoughts and Writings</title>
  <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-11-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/" />
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Armin Ronacher's personal blog about programming, games and random thoughts that come to his mind.</subtitle>
  <generator>Werkzeug</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">A Europe For Our Children</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/5/18/for-our-children</id>
    <updated>2016-05-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/5/18/for-our-children" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most of the readers of this blog are not from Europe, let alone Austria,
the country I was born in.  As such I'm not sure how many will actually
care about Austrian politics here, especially if it's a lengthy post.  But
I would still like if you read it because I think the topic is important
and not just because of Austria.  Our problems here are not just ours,
they are a general issue that affects all of Europe and the western world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since you are probably in no way familiar with Austrian politics or the
situation in the country I want to give you a brief overview.  Austria has
recovered very quickly from the war torn country it was after World War 2
and emerged as one of the most powerful economies of Europe if looked at
on a GDP per capita basis.  It underwent a conversion from an agricultural
country with some tourism attached to being dominated by the service
industry and producing technology and parts (the economical tree map looks
confusing because it's so heavily diversified).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However as great as the country has developed after the wars and as
profitable the creation of the Eurozone was, there was an end to this
positive trend and it came with the financial crisis of 2007/2008
(although with a bit of a delay).  The economy did recover, but it did not
do it to the extent people wanted.  At the same time necessary reforms
were not implemented (or not implemented in the right ways) and as a
result the country has suffered major blows in the last few years.  From a
personal point of view I cannot stress enough how disappointed I am that
many of my collegues went to other countries and started their companies
there or work there.  But it would be foolish to blame politics on this
alone.  This is as much a problem of politics as it is a problem of
culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now reached the point where cheap and populist ideas like reducing
social welfare for non citizens gets popular support.  In this environment
right wing parties emerge and this sunday Austrians will probably elect
the first right wing leader of the country since the end of World War 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But politics not what I want to talk about.  What I want to talk about is
the erosion of civilized discourse in Austria and I think in all of
Europe.  A large part of the general public are unable to have civilized
discussions on the bases of facts and instead conspiracies and emotions
take over and this is something that extends to politicians in Austria as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-symptoms-and-problems&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Symptoms and Problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the emotional state of the country you can see a few
symptoms and problems that help the populists to raise to power:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inability (or unwillingness) to learn and understand&lt;/strong&gt; how Austria and
the world changed in the last few years.  I think this is a big one of the
people who want to leave the European Union and do similar crazy things
to the Austrian economy.  We're so intertwined with it, that I doubt
anyone can predict what would happen as a consequence of leaving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparing things that cannot directly be compared&lt;/strong&gt; is a very related
problem. As an example the Euro might have been a mistake for Germany
but that does not mean that the Euro was not a profit for Austria.  We
were pegged to the Mark before, for us not much changed.  If anything the
situation improved because we're an export nation and our export partners
are other European countries and if they also use the Euro they cannot
harm our exports by devaluing their own currencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But despite the fact it's so very hard to compare countries because they
are so fundamentally differently structured - yet people will still do
it in conversations.  Switzerland is heralded as the great example of
continental Europe in Austria but it's so specific out of history that
it's incredible hard to copy or imitate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not being able consider the other side&lt;/strong&gt;. I am shocked sometimes what
people here in Austria think the US are like.  The idea that both
Europeans and Americans might have very similar fears or hopes for TTIP
for instance does not seem to exist here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear of change&lt;/strong&gt;. I think this is a typical Austrian problem but to
smaller extent it probably exists elsewhere too. Everything new is
torpedoed until it cannot be avoided any more because every single other
country already did it before. That applies to smoking bans as much as
to embracing of credit cards, online services, acceptance of
homosexuality, Sunday shopping, flexible working hours and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broad categorization&lt;/strong&gt;. I think Austrians are masters at giving
good/bad labels to large masses of people based on some categorization
instead of considering the individual.  Refugees are either good or bad,
the industry is good or bad, corporations are good or bad, immigrants
are good or bad. That individually a refugee could be good or bad is
impossible to comprehend in the general discourse and if someone does
bring it up, it often gets dismissed as an outlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inability to give credit&lt;/strong&gt;. This is particularly a problem in Austrian
politics. It's one party against the other and never ever would a ruling
party give an opposition party credit or the other way round. Likewise
would social democratic voters never give conservative parties credit
for something or the other way round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-root-causes&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Root Causes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what causes this behavior?  I think Austria's history has a lot to do
with it.  In the recent history there were conservatives versus social
democrats.  Combined with the fact that after the war Austria emerged not
only as a loser but also has one with a lot of baggage due to the support
to national socialism and the complicated way to deal with it after the
war.  As such the population was always split in two on this level.
However they could unity at least somewhat by voting for one of the two
large centrist parties.  Because the country was doing really well, there
was no reason to reevaluate this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However when disaster struck this rift became bigger instead of smaller
and particular with this upcoming presidential election only the most
extreme candidates made it into the run-off. Voters did not vote for
people they believed in as much as they voted by using tactics against
predictions.  This now has lead to one the ugliest pre-elections I have
seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics are no longer about doing the right thing but defending
principles, even if they are completely unfounded.  Even though everybody
says they have the best for Austrian in mind everyone is so stuck to their
own opinion that not a single meter of compromise can be achieved.
Newspapers paint scary pictures of the different outcomes of the election,
how the country will be torn, how one candidate would mean European
sanctions and how the other candidate would mean the end of a functioning
society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;a-path-forward&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are clearly many things wrong in this country but so is it
everywhere else.  We're not alone with the changes in the world and we
cannot fall back to local solutions for these problems.  But likewise can
we not pretend that problems don't exist.  This behavior of ruling parties
has helped the rise of the populists.  It does not help to pretend that
immigration without integration does not contribute to problems in
society.  We need a more honest approach with more talking to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few days ago we got &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian_Kern&quot;&gt;a new chancellor&lt;/a&gt; and he has indicated that
he wants to end the course of confrontation his predecessors had.  This
has been supported by all other parties other than the right wing FPOe.  I
hope they reconsider and also want to constructively work together with
the rest of the government to lead the country forward and to restore a
positive way of thinking rather than the fear that has been going around
for the last years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This however is not something that is a problem that needs to be solved in
government.  This is a problem that we as people in that country have and
we need to talk to each other more.  If we talk more to each other I hope
it becomes clear that we share many core values, we just don't always
agree on all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to my friends in Austria: please vote. But more than that: please
accept that if the outcome is not what you wanted, that it does not mean
the end of the country as you know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Be Careful About What You Dislike</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/11/5/be-careful-about-what-you-dislike</id>
    <updated>2016-11-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2016/11/5/be-careful-about-what-you-dislike" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last few months I keep making the same observation over and over again
in various different contexts: that whenever you are confronted with a
very strong opinion about a topic, reasonable discussions about the topic
often involve arguments that have long become outdated or are no longer
strictly relevant to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I mean by that is that given a controversial topic, a valid argument
for one side of the other is being repeated by a crowd of people that once
heard it, even after that argument stops being valid.  This happens because
often the general situation changed and the argument references a reality
that no longer exists in the same form.  Instead of reevaluating the
environment however, goalposts are moved to restore the general sentiment
of the opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you a practical example of this problem I can just go by a topic I
have a very strong opinion about: Python 3.  When Python 3 was not a huge
thing yet I started having conversations with people in the community
about the problems I see with splitting the community and complexity of
porting.  Not just that, I also kept bringing up general questions about
some of the text and byte decisions.  I started doing talks about the
topic and write blog articles that kept being shared.  Nowadays when I go
to a conference I very quickly end up in conversations where other
developers come to me and see me as the &amp;quot;Does not like Python 3 guy&amp;quot;.
While I still am not a friend of some of the decisions in Python 3 I am
very much aware that Python 3 in 2016 is a very different Python 3 than 6
years ago or earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I myself campaigned for some changes to Python 3 that made it
possible to achieve better ports (like the reintroduction of the &lt;cite&gt;u&lt;/cite&gt;
prefix on Unicode string literals) and the bulk of my libraries work on
Python 3 for many years now.  It's a fact that in 2016 the problems that
people have with Python 3 are different than they used to have before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to very interesting conversations where I can have a highly
technical conversation about a very specific issue with Python 3 and
thoughts about how to do it differently or deal with it (like some of the
less obvious consequences of the new text storage model) and another
person joins into the conversation with an argument against Python 3 that
has long stropped being valid.  Why?  Because there is a cost towards
porting to Python 3 and a chance is not seen.  This means that a person
with a general negativity towards Python 3 would seek me out and try to
reaffirm their opposition to a port to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same thing is happening with JavaScript where there is a general negative
sentiment about programming in it but not everybody is having good
arguments for it.  There are some that actually program a lot in it and
dislike specific things about the current state of the ecosystem, but
generally acknowledge that the language is evolving, and then there are
those that take advantage of unhappiness and bring their heavily outdated
opposition against JavaScript into a conversation just to reaffirm their
own opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is hardly confined to the programming world.  I made the same
discovery about CETA.  CETA is a free trade agreement between the European
Union and Canada and it had the misfortune of being negotiated at the same
time as the more controversial TTIP with the US.  The story goes roughly
like this: TTIP was negotiated in secrecy (as all trade agreements are)
and there were strong disagreements between what the EU and what the US
thought trade should look like.  Those differences were about food safety
standards and other highly sensitive topics.  Various organizations on
both the left and right extremes of the political scale started to grab
any remotely controversial information that leaked out to shift the public
opinion towards negativity to TTIP.  Then the entire thing spiraled out of
control: people not only railed against TTIP but took their opposition
and looked for similar contracts and found CETA.  Since both are trade
agreements there is naturally a lot of common ground between them.  The
subtleties where quickly lost.  Where the initial arguments against TTIP
were food standards, public services and intransparent ISDS courts many of
the critics failed to realize that CETA fundamentally was a different
beast.  Not only was it already a much improved agreement from the start,
but it kept being modified from the initial public version of it to the
one that was finally sent to national parliaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However despite what I would have expected: that critics go in and
acknowledge that their criticism was being heard instead slowly moved the
goalposts.  At this point there is so much emotion and misinformation in
the general community that the goalpost moved all the way to not
supporting further free trade at all.  In the general conversation about
ISDS and standards many people brought introduced their own opinions about
free trade and their dislike towards corporations and multinationals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This I assume is human behavior.  Admitting that you might be wrong is
hard enough, but it's even harder when you had validation that you were
right in the past.  In particular that an argument against something might
no longer be valid because that something has changed in the meantime is
hard.  I'm not sure what the solution to this is but I definitely realized
in the few years on my own behavior that one needs to be more careful
about stating strong opinions in public.  At the same time however I think
we should all be more careful dispelling misinformation in conversations
even if the general mood supports your opinion.  As an example while
emotionally I like hearing stories about how JavaScript's packaging causes
pain to developers since I experienced it first hand, I know from a
rational point of view that the ecosystem is improving a tremendous
speeds.  Yes I have been burned by npm but it's not like this is not
tremendously improving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that has been put to paper once is hard to remove from people's
minds.  In particular in the technological context technology moves so
fast that very likely something you read once might no longer be up to
date as little as six months later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I suppose my proposal to readers is not to fall into that trap and to
assume that the environment around oneself keeps on changing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">On Countries, Citizenships, Residence and Paying Taxes</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2015/8/9/on-countries-and-citizenships</id>
    <updated>2015-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2015/8/9/on-countries-and-citizenships" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like many software engineers my life involved moving from one country to
another for work.  Since that moment this whole concept of relocation
fascinated me because almost everyone in my circle of friends ended up in
a place far from where they came but their stories were different.
I learned that the topic of relocation and immigration is a very complex
and diverse one.  How widely different the experience can be for different
people!  Most interesting about this however is how little people not
affected by this understand the complexities of being an immigrant in
another country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my experience of moving to another country was the easiest
imaginable, it was harder for my wife.  How different immigration can be
is hard to imagine from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since immigration is a big topic again I figured I might share some of my
experience on the topic to shed some light on how all that stuff actually
works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important part is to understand the legal basis for pretty much
all topics related to entering and leaving a country and the permits.
This is surprisingly complex because of the huge variety of different
terms for related topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;docutils&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Citizenship&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Citizenship is typically what you get at birth and it makes you the
citizen of a certain country.  In the majority of countries being a
citizen gives you certain rights but also obligations.  For instance
in Austria citizenship gives you the right to vote, but you are
required to defend your country.  Citizenship also almost always gives
you the right to live in a country though there might be further
requirements.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Multiple Citizenships&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This refers to the idea of holding two (or more) active citizenships.
This is one of the more complex topics because of how different
countries approach this.  On the one hand are countries like Austria
which have the concept of dual citizenships but make it very hard to
hold multiple.  On the other there are countries like the US which do
not recognize other citizenships at all but will not prevent you from
holding multiple.  Lastly there are countries which outlaw multiple
citizenships altogether.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Visas&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;If you are not a citizen of a country you might need a visa to enter
or leave a country.  Visas in itself however do not necessarily give
you the right to actually be in a country.  A good example for that
would be a person who immigrates into a European country for work from
a country with a passport that requires you to have a visa.  In that
case you need a visa to cross the border and then you need a permit to
stay / permit to work.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Permits&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Permits come in different flavours and not all countries have the same
approach to them.  In most countries there are permits to stay and
separate permits to work and sometimes there are residence permits
which work differently.  In Austria for instance there are permits
called “Aufenthaltstitel” which literally translates to “entitlement
for stay” which also usually comes with an indication if you are
allowed to become part of the workforce or not.  For instance a family
member permit gives you the right to work whereas a permit for stay
for students will only give you limited permissions for working.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Passports&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;Passports are travel documents and means to identify yourself
internationally.  As of a few years ago any person travelling will
need one of those which includes little children.  Interestingly
however passports are a lot more complex than you might think because
they are not directly linked to citizenship.  More about this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;last&quot;&gt;A passport gets you across a border and in many cases can act as an
universally accepted way to proof something about yourself.  For most
states in the world the passports follow a generally accepted format
which makes them very convenient and they are on of the few documents
you never need to translate.  Because of this, they will become your
best friend when you are not at home though they are by no means the
only document you need to reside in another country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;relationship-citizenship-and-passport&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relationship Citizenship and Passport&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people would assume that having a passport of one country makes you a
citizen thereof.  That however is not at all correct.  There are different
reasons for this and I can't go into all here.  The biggest reason why you
might have a passport of a country you are not a citizen of is because you
are a stateless person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people in the world once they hold a citizenship they cannot
become stateless.  The reason for this is that there are international
treaties where if ratified in a country you cannot lose your citizenship
unless you acquire another one.  There are some countries where this is
not the case.  The United States being the most popular of them.  A US
national can give up their US citizenship and become a stateless person
this way.  The reason this works is because you do not need to be a US
citizen to be a US national.  For instance people born in American Samoa
are US nationals but they are not US citizens.  This is also the part
where citizenship and nationality becomes unclear.  A person born in
American Samoa will for all intents and purposes be seen as a US citizen
as their passport will indicate that they have US nationality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand there are many stateless people living in Estona and
Lativa who are officially stateless.  The reason for this is that they are
Russian speaking and are either not entitled to Estonian or Latvian
citizenship or have no interest in applying for one.  They are issued a
special passport for stateless people which however some some special
powers an Estonian passport does not have: they can travel to Russia visa
free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;how-do-i-migrate&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Do I Migrate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This for many is the million dollar question.  How can I immigrate in a
foreign country?  Generally this question heavily depends on your own
citizenship and the laws of the country you want to become a resident of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the most common ways to immigrate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;docutils&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Freedom of Movement&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;Sometimes you are entitled just like that to live in another country
like a citizen of that country would be.  This for instance is the
case within the European Union.  If you are German but you feel like
living in the Czech Republic, you can do so.  Just head there and
you're done.  That's not entirely true, you still need to do some
paper work in some cases (like registering etc.), but there is no rule
that prevents you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;last&quot;&gt;This is by far the easiest route but it's restricted to a certain
population of the world, and there is good chance you as a reader are
not in that group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Marry a Citizen&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;Marriage is still the best way to get a permit of residence and it's
becoming an even better by the day because the requirements are so
stict nowadays.  However marriage does not immediately give you
residence and most people will probably have noticed that.  As an
example in order for me and my wife (who is not Austrian) to legally
live together with our child in Austria we need to have household
income of 17.500 EUR per year after taxes.  That does not sound like a
lot, but for many people it's not the easiest thing to show,
especially because those earnings need to exist regardless of the
outcome of your residence application.  For most people this means
showing that you have that much in cash available as you probably do
not live in the country yet to demonstrate a regular income through
paychecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;last&quot;&gt;In the United Kingdom the income requirement is currently 18.600 GBP /
year and you need to show income for 2.5 years.  Which means that if
you want to show it in savings, you need to have at least 62.500 GBP
on an account somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Be Exceptional&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The only other way to immigrate is typically to be exceptional.  In
most countries this is either by being rich enough to invest into the
country and get residence or citizenship in the process or by being
extraordinary intelligent or in demand.  This works well for engineers
because engineers are in demand in almost all places.  However that is
no guarantee yet, as in most countries visas and permits are
restricted by numbers and there is a certain amount of luck
requirement to get one.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Become a Citizen&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Most people cannot become a citizen from one day to another, but
sometimes they can.  In that case that is the way to go.  Typically
this is done by a prior claim to citizenship that you forgot about
(for instance to be born to a parent with a certain citizenship).
This most of the time is only possible for as long as you did not turn
18 yet.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Claim Asylum&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;In certain situations you might be getting away with claiming asylum.
Pretty sure the chances that you are a reader of this blog and you
quality for this route are very dim.  Asylum is restricted to people
who come from situations where their life is in danger.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;legal-immigration-is-hard&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Legal Immigration is Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal immigration is expensive and a lot of work.  Besides the proof of
income (which just requires you to have money), there is a lot of time and
effort required.  All the documents you need (birth certificate, proof of
being in good legal standing, citizen certificate, proof of registration
in the original country, prior academic records, drivers license, etc.)
need to be apostiled or otherwise made work for international usage and
translated.  In some country many of those documents can only be retrieved
in a single place and then you need to go through notaries to get them
attested.  All steps need to be done in one exact order as each border
crossing needs to be planned and there is time involved in the paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that you often need to pass language exams so there is some
learning to do.  In Austria for instance you have to leave the country if
you cannot show German on an A2 level and you cannot even apply without
A1.  There are some exceptions to the rule (for instance this does not
apply to asylum seekers or people immigrating via freedom of movement) but
for the most part everybody has to go through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally:  Where do you pay taxes?  In most countries you pay taxes in the
country you have your primary residence.  However there are some
exceptions.  The US will tax you no matter where in the world you are, but
they will try to not double tax you for some time.  The US will also tax
you if you stop being a citizen and they think you relinquished your
citizenship to dodge taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-illegal-route&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Illegal Route&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people I met over the years just never legally immigrated somewhere.
That however does not mean that they are illegally in the country.  It can
also mean that they just never immigrated to begin with and just hop from
country to country.  They are there as submarines either by pretending to
be tourists and regularly changing the place of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit different from the traditional method of not crossing the
border much which many migrant workers do.  This however can turn terrible
the moment someone catches you.  Overstaying your permitted time in
Schengen for instance will lock you out for 5 years from almost the entire
European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

