<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">Armin Ronacher's Thoughts and Writings</title>
  <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom</id>
  <updated>2015-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/" />
  <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <subtitle type="text">Armin Ronacher's personal blog about programming, games and random thoughts that come to his mind.</subtitle>
  <generator>Werkzeug</generator>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Emotional Programming in Open Source</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/11/28/emotional-programming</id>
    <updated>2013-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2013/11/28/emotional-programming" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that one of the biggest reasons for the perceived high
quality of lots of Open Source code is that the developers are generally
happier writing it.  Lots of people in the Open Source community develop
something that solve particular problems they have themselves.  But what
happens when you no longer have problems to solve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it quite hard this year to work on my own projects because the
bug trackers were full of things I personally did not really care about.
The things I wrote over the last few years all work so well &lt;em&gt;for me&lt;/em&gt;, that
I don't need to fix problems or add things.  When there is something that
needs fixing, I will work on it, but otherwise I don't necessarily get the
motivation to work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big reason for this is that I need to split my available time between
work, my open source projects, learning new things and private life.
Lately when I open the bug-tracker for my projects I get an overwhelming
feeling of failure.  github shows me 500 unprocessed notifications and my
inbox is now up to 100 unreplied mails, many of which I regret not
replying, but after a while it seems pointless to reply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unfortunate truth is that some things in my life started acting on
their own without me having much control over it.  Somehow it happened
that on PyPI I am (was?) one of the authors with the most downloads and
split across multiple projects and that sort-of happened by itself.  It's
incredible motivating to see people using my software but at the same time
I fundamentally failed on reducing the bus factor so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I have spent a lot more time with keeping Splash Damage and
Fireteam stuff running than with my Open Source projects.  Not because
there was a lot of need for it, but because I had more fun with it.  I
mentioned this up before, but the whole porting to Python 3 thing has
killed so much motivation for working on my project for me.  I cannot use
Python 3 in practice and having to deal with issues I don't have myself is
one of the most frustrating things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is however also always the biggest advantage of Open Source,
especially if it's BSD licensed.  Even though the project's author might
at one point not be contributing as much to the project as before, you
have full access to everything.  You will never end up in an unfixable
situation.  This is in a strong contrast to how the proprietary world
looks like.  Commercial funding in a project might generally keep it more
active, at least for as long as money flows, but commercial interests
might not be yours.  Companies get acquired, licensing deals change and
you might be left from one day to the other in a situation where you need
to switch technology because it's just no longer available.  I have seen
this happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that in mind I am currently trying to get things sorted out to
everybody's satisfaction.  It's unacceptable that issues hang around
unprocessed this long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Source can be hard sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">On Countries, Citizenships, Residence and Paying Taxes</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2015/8/9/on-countries-and-citizenships</id>
    <updated>2015-08-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2015/8/9/on-countries-and-citizenships" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like many software engineers my life involved moving from one country to
another for work.  Since that moment this whole concept of relocation
fascinated me because almost everyone in my circle of friends ended up in
a place far from where they came but their stories were different.
I learned that the topic of relocation and immigration is a very complex
and diverse one.  How widely different the experience can be for different
people!  Most interesting about this however is how little people not
affected by this understand the complexities of being an immigrant in
another country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While my experience of moving to another country was the easiest
imaginable, it was harder for my wife.  How different immigration can be
is hard to imagine from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since immigration is a big topic again I figured I might share some of my
experience on the topic to shed some light on how all that stuff actually
works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important part is to understand the legal basis for pretty much
all topics related to entering and leaving a country and the permits.
This is surprisingly complex because of the huge variety of different
terms for related topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;docutils&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Citizenship&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Citizenship is typically what you get at birth and it makes you the
citizen of a certain country.  In the majority of countries being a
citizen gives you certain rights but also obligations.  For instance
in Austria citizenship gives you the right to vote, but you are
required to defend your country.  Citizenship also almost always gives
you the right to live in a country though there might be further
requirements.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Multiple Citizenships&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This refers to the idea of holding two (or more) active citizenships.
This is one of the more complex topics because of how different
countries approach this.  On the one hand are countries like Austria
which have the concept of dual citizenships but make it very hard to
hold multiple.  On the other there are countries like the US which do
not recognize other citizenships at all but will not prevent you from
holding multiple.  Lastly there are countries which outlaw multiple
citizenships altogether.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Visas&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;If you are not a citizen of a country you might need a visa to enter
or leave a country.  Visas in itself however do not necessarily give
you the right to actually be in a country.  A good example for that
would be a person who immigrates into a European country for work from
a country with a passport that requires you to have a visa.  In that
case you need a visa to cross the border and then you need a permit to
stay / permit to work.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Permits&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Permits come in different flavours and not all countries have the same
approach to them.  In most countries there are permits to stay and
separate permits to work and sometimes there are residence permits
which work differently.  In Austria for instance there are permits
called “Aufenthaltstitel” which literally translates to “entitlement
for stay” which also usually comes with an indication if you are
allowed to become part of the workforce or not.  For instance a family
member permit gives you the right to work whereas a permit for stay
for students will only give you limited permissions for working.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Passports&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;Passports are travel documents and means to identify yourself
internationally.  As of a few years ago any person travelling will
need one of those which includes little children.  Interestingly
however passports are a lot more complex than you might think because
they are not directly linked to citizenship.  More about this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;last&quot;&gt;A passport gets you across a border and in many cases can act as an
universally accepted way to proof something about yourself.  For most
states in the world the passports follow a generally accepted format
which makes them very convenient and they are on of the few documents
you never need to translate.  Because of this, they will become your
best friend when you are not at home though they are by no means the
only document you need to reside in another country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;relationship-citizenship-and-passport&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relationship Citizenship and Passport&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people would assume that having a passport of one country makes you a
citizen thereof.  That however is not at all correct.  There are different
reasons for this and I can't go into all here.  The biggest reason why you
might have a passport of a country you are not a citizen of is because you
are a stateless person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most people in the world once they hold a citizenship they cannot
become stateless.  The reason for this is that there are international
treaties where if ratified in a country you cannot lose your citizenship
unless you acquire another one.  There are some countries where this is
not the case.  The United States being the most popular of them.  A US
national can give up their US citizenship and become a stateless person
this way.  The reason this works is because you do not need to be a US
citizen to be a US national.  For instance people born in American Samoa
are US nationals but they are not US citizens.  This is also the part
where citizenship and nationality becomes unclear.  A person born in
American Samoa will for all intents and purposes be seen as a US citizen
as their passport will indicate that they have US nationality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand there are many stateless people living in Estona and
Lativa who are officially stateless.  The reason for this is that they are
Russian speaking and are either not entitled to Estonian or Latvian
citizenship or have no interest in applying for one.  They are issued a
special passport for stateless people which however some some special
powers an Estonian passport does not have: they can travel to Russia visa
free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;how-do-i-migrate&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Do I Migrate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This for many is the million dollar question.  How can I immigrate in a
foreign country?  Generally this question heavily depends on your own
citizenship and the laws of the country you want to become a resident of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the most common ways to immigrate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class=&quot;docutils&quot;&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Freedom of Movement&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;Sometimes you are entitled just like that to live in another country
like a citizen of that country would be.  This for instance is the
case within the European Union.  If you are German but you feel like
living in the Czech Republic, you can do so.  Just head there and
you're done.  That's not entirely true, you still need to do some
paper work in some cases (like registering etc.), but there is no rule
that prevents you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;last&quot;&gt;This is by far the easiest route but it's restricted to a certain
population of the world, and there is good chance you as a reader are
not in that group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Marry a Citizen&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;first&quot;&gt;Marriage is still the best way to get a permit of residence and it's
becoming an even better by the day because the requirements are so
stict nowadays.  However marriage does not immediately give you
residence and most people will probably have noticed that.  As an
example in order for me and my wife (who is not Austrian) to legally
live together with our child in Austria we need to have household
income of 17.500 EUR per year after taxes.  That does not sound like a
lot, but for many people it's not the easiest thing to show,
especially because those earnings need to exist regardless of the
outcome of your residence application.  For most people this means
showing that you have that much in cash available as you probably do
not live in the country yet to demonstrate a regular income through
paychecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;last&quot;&gt;In the United Kingdom the income requirement is currently 18.600 GBP /
year and you need to show income for 2.5 years.  Which means that if
you want to show it in savings, you need to have at least 62.500 GBP
on an account somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Be Exceptional&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The only other way to immigrate is typically to be exceptional.  In
most countries this is either by being rich enough to invest into the
country and get residence or citizenship in the process or by being
extraordinary intelligent or in demand.  This works well for engineers
because engineers are in demand in almost all places.  However that is
no guarantee yet, as in most countries visas and permits are
restricted by numbers and there is a certain amount of luck
requirement to get one.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Become a Citizen&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Most people cannot become a citizen from one day to another, but
sometimes they can.  In that case that is the way to go.  Typically
this is done by a prior claim to citizenship that you forgot about
(for instance to be born to a parent with a certain citizenship).
This most of the time is only possible for as long as you did not turn
18 yet.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Claim Asylum&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;In certain situations you might be getting away with claiming asylum.
Pretty sure the chances that you are a reader of this blog and you
quality for this route are very dim.  Asylum is restricted to people
who come from situations where their life is in danger.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;legal-immigration-is-hard&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Legal Immigration is Hard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal immigration is expensive and a lot of work.  Besides the proof of
income (which just requires you to have money), there is a lot of time and
effort required.  All the documents you need (birth certificate, proof of
being in good legal standing, citizen certificate, proof of registration
in the original country, prior academic records, drivers license, etc.)
need to be apostiled or otherwise made work for international usage and
translated.  In some country many of those documents can only be retrieved
in a single place and then you need to go through notaries to get them
attested.  All steps need to be done in one exact order as each border
crossing needs to be planned and there is time involved in the paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that you often need to pass language exams so there is some
learning to do.  In Austria for instance you have to leave the country if
you cannot show German on an A2 level and you cannot even apply without
A1.  There are some exceptions to the rule (for instance this does not
apply to asylum seekers or people immigrating via freedom of movement) but
for the most part everybody has to go through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally:  Where do you pay taxes?  In most countries you pay taxes in the
country you have your primary residence.  However there are some
exceptions.  The US will tax you no matter where in the world you are, but
they will try to not double tax you for some time.  The US will also tax
you if you stop being a citizen and they think you relinquished your
citizenship to dodge taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;the-illegal-route&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Illegal Route&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people I met over the years just never legally immigrated somewhere.
That however does not mean that they are illegally in the country.  It can
also mean that they just never immigrated to begin with and just hop from
country to country.  They are there as submarines either by pretending to
be tourists and regularly changing the place of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a bit different from the traditional method of not crossing the
border much which many migrant workers do.  This however can turn terrible
the moment someone catches you.  Overstaying your permitted time in
Schengen for instance will lock you out for 5 years from almost the entire
European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry xml:base="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/feed.atom">
    <title type="text">Status Update 2010</title>
    <id>http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2010/1/6/status-update-2010</id>
    <updated>2010-01-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <link href="http://lucumr.pocoo.org/2010/1/6/status-update-2010" />
    <author>
      <name>Armin Ronacher</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the archives, the activity in this blog was rather
low the last couple of weeks. But not only the blog, also my visible
programming activity and everything related. There are a couple of
reason for that but unfortunately I'm not entirely sure how this will
change in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University turned out to be boring and stressful at the same time and is
the main limiting factor of my productivity. While at the same time many
courses bore or frustrate me, there is still a lot of stuff that has to
be delivered or learned for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is the primary reason for not being active at all, there are
a couple of other reasons as well. What I spend most of my time with the
last couple of years was certainly Open Source (I guess even free
software), Python and web applications. For a time I am interested in
other topics as well, I just never had the impression that I would be
able to learn was has to be learned to succeed at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don't know, but without trying I will never know. So my Python /
Webdev activity will most likely stay as low as it currently is for a
while. That however does not mean that my projects will be unmaintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;project-maintenance&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's happening to the projects in the near future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;werkzeug-s-future&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Werkzeug's Future&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this little bugger will certainly get a new release soon. I was
actually planning a release before the beginning of the new year but
there are a couple of things that I want to have sorted out first. I was
planning to move the debugger together with a couple of things into a
new library called Flickzeug, but because I don't think I will
personally need debugging tools any time soon, I will put that plan on
hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone is interested in helping out there, just drop me a line and I
will help you as good as I can. The design of the library is pretty much
finished, just the implementation is unfinished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until something for Flickzeug is planned, the debugging component will
stay in Werkzeug and not be deprecated. The same cannot be said about
the Werkzeug templates however. Because it depends on a library that
goes away in Python 3 I will only deprecate it for future Werkzeug
Python 3 versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also my biggest grief at the moment. I am totally unhappy how
Python is developing currently and especially with the implementation of
Python 3 and the plans for it. Graham Dumpleton is doing an insanely
great job with maintaining mod_wsgi and I am sure whatever he decides on
for Python 3's WSGI will become the standard everybody is using. And I
trust him enough that I know whatever is chosen, is an acceptable
solution everybody can be happy with. Until then however, I do not plan
to port Werkzeug to Python 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;jinja&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jinja&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jinja is a little bit more complicated. The hg tip should work on Python
3 already if you run it through 2to3, so with the next release we should
have acceptable builtin Python 3 support. What keeps me from releasing a
new version is that the compiler has a couple of scoping issues that
arrive from edge cases where Jinja scoping does not properly translate
to Python scoping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that would not be an issue if I could generate bytecode directly,
but that unfortunately is not portable and does not work on the
appengine at all, so I can only add further workarounds into the code
generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I am looking for code that breaks on Jinja2 tip and come up
with solutions for these edge cases. If you have templates that break on
tip, let me know and file tickets for those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;zine&quot;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Zine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is the most tricky project. When I started working on Zine I
was extremely motived doing that, mostly because at that time WordPress
was really weak and easy to catch up to. However Zine is still a one man
project and because it is built in Python it is mostly interesting for
other Python developers and as such missing its market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hg version is a lot better than the latest release so what I will do
is integrating the missing changes into it and release a new version at
the beginning of February. From that point onwards however I have no
plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;why-all-that&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why all that&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why the sudden switch away from what I did the last years? It's not
that I lost motivation in general for what web development but I don't
want to limit myself to that area. There is more I am interested in and
because I picked the wrong studies all over again I won't learn enough I
will have to start learning that next to my regular studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Gaynor wrote an essay about &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://lazypython.blogspot.com/2009/12/few-thoughts-on-education.html&quot;&gt;education&lt;/a&gt;
a while ago to which I wanted to respond, but I never had the time to.
Lately however that comes back more and more to me because the situation
in Austria regarding education and university is currently just weird
for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically it boils down to me at the same time being incredible unhappy
with the way university works in Austria but finding myself over and
over again in the situation where I have to defend the system against
other stupid students that think it's a good idea to &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.austriantimes.at/news/General_News/2009-12-21/19038/Student_protesters_%27shocked%27_after_auditorium_evictions&quot;&gt;occupy a large
auditorium&lt;/a&gt;
to get more money from the state (and by doing so disrupting other
students whose exams get relocated, access to library denied and so
forth).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;call-for-volunteers&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Call for Volunteers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a while ago there were a couple of people contributing code to
various Pocoo projects. This is still true but even though the number of
people using Werkzeug, Jinja2 and Zine increased (not mentioning
Pygments here which Georg maintains) the number of patches and active
developers decreased. This is unfortunate because right now I'm pretty
much alone on these and working alone means that in times where I have
few time to spare, the amound of new features, improvements and
everything declines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two projects of mine (CleverCSS and GHRML) either found new owners by
sending me a mail or got some better maintained branches on github and I
would love to either hand over the project completely (including the
pypi page) or getting you on the pocoo team and giving you commit access
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Werkzeug, Jinja2 and Zine my plan is to clean up the trackers a lot
so that it's easier to work on small tasks which hopefully will both
enable external contributions and make it possible for me to work on
these next to what I will do otherwise :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;happy-new-2010&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Happy new 2010&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for all of you, a Happy new 2010 and may it have more, and more
stable releases, than 2009!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>

